[
  {
    "question": "Is the computer business as ruthless as it appears to be?",
    "response": "No, not at this point. To me, the situation is like a river. When the river is moving swiftly there isn't a lot of moss and algae in it, but when it slows down and becomes stagnant, a lot of stuff grows in the river and it gets very murky. I view the cutthroat political nature of things very much like that. And right now our business is moving very swiftly. The water's pretty clear and there's not a lot of ruthlessness. There's a lot of room for innovation.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "Do you consider yourself the new astronaut, the new American hero?",
    "response": "No, no, no. I'm just a guy who probably should have been a semi-talented poet on the Left Bank. I sort of got sidetracked here. The space guys, the astronauts, were techies to start with. John Glenn didn't read Rimbaud, you know; but you talk to some of the people in the computer business now and they're very well grounded in the philosophical traditions of the last 100 years and the sociological traditions of the '60s. There's something going on here, there's something that is changing the world and this is the epicenter. It's probably closest to Washington during the Kennedy era or something like that. Now I start sounding like Gary Hart.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "You don't like him?",
    "response": "Hart? I don't dislike him. I met him about a year ago and my impression was that there was not a great deal of substance there.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "So who do you want to see...",
    "response": "I've never voted for a presidential candidate. I've never voted in my whole life.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "Do you think it's unfair that people out here in Silicon Valley are generally labeled nerds?",
    "response": "Of course. I think it's an antiquated notion. There were people in the '60s who were like that and even in the early '70s, but now they're not that way. Now they're the people who would have been poets had they lived in the '60s. And they're looking at computers as their medium of expression rather than language, rather than being a mathematician and using mathematics, rather than, you know, writing social theories.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "What do people do for fun out here? I've noticed that an awful lot of those who work for you either play music or are extremely interested in it.",
    "response": "Oh yes. And most of them are also left-handed, whatever that means. Almost all of the really great technical people in computers that I've known are left-handed. Isn't that odd?",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "Are you left-handed?",
    "response": "I'm ambidextrous.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "But why music?",
    "response": "When you want to understand something that's never been understood before, what you have to do is construct conceptual scaffolding. And if you're trying to design a computer you will literally immerse yourself in the thousands of details necessary; all of a sudden, as the scaffolding gets set up high enough, it will all become clearer and clearer that's when the breakthrough starts. It is a rhythmic experience, or it is an experience where everything's related to everything else and it's all intertwined. And it's such a fragile, delicate experience that it's very much like music. But you could never describe it to anyone.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "In 1977 you said that computers were answers in search of questions. Has that changed?",
    "response": "Well, the types of computers we have today are tools. They're responders: you ask a computer to do something and it will do it. The next stage is going to be computers as \"agents.\" In other words, it will be as if there's a little person inside that box who starts to anticipate what you want. Rather than help you, it will start to guide you through large amounts of information. It will almost be like you have a little friend inside that box. I think the computer as an agent will start to mature in the late '80s, early '90s.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "You once talked about wanting to have a computer that could sit in a child's playroom and be the child's playmate.",
    "response": "Forget about the child—I'd like one myself! I've always thought it would be really wonderful to have a little box, a sort of slate that you could carry along with you. You'd get one of these things maybe when you were 10 years old, and somehow you'd turn it on and it would say, you know, \"Where am I?\" And you'd somehow tell it you were in California and it would say, \"Oh, who are you?\" \"My name's Steven.\"\"Really? How old are you?\"\"I'm 10.\"\"What are we doing here?\"\"Well, we're in recess and we have to go back to class.\"\"What's class?\" You'd start to teach it about yourself. And it would just keep storing all this information about you and maybe it would recognize that every Friday afternoon you like to do something special, and maybe you'd like it to help you with this routine. So about the third time it asks you: \"Well, would you like me to do this for you every Friday?\" You say: \"Yes,\" and before long it becomes an incredibly powerful helper. It goes with you everywhere you go. It knows most of the raw information in your life that you'd like to keep, but then starts to make connections between things, and one day when you're 18 and you've just split up with your girlfriend it says: \"You know, Steve, the same thing has happened three times in a row.\"",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "You grew up in an odd place here, surrounded by all this technology.",
    "response": "Yes. The guy next door to my parents' place was doing some of the foundation research on solar cells. Actually, I had a pretty normal childhood. It's nice growing up here. I mean the air was very clean; it was a little like being out in the country.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "As a kid, were you already conscious of some sort of social structure forming, that there were people who were in the silicon business and there were people who weren't?",
    "response": "Hmmm, no. See, there wasn't such a thing as the silicon business back in the early '60s when I was between the ages of 5 and 10. There was electronics. Silicon, as a distinct item from the whole of electronics, didn't really occur until the '70s.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "How did it affect the culture here?",
    "response": "Well, Silicon Valley has evolved into the heart of the electronics industry—which is the second largest industry in the world and will soon pass agriculture and become the largest. So Silicon Valley is destined to become a technological metropolis and there are pluses and minuses to that. It's very sad in a way because this valley was probably the closest thing to the Garden of Eden at one point in time.No more.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why?",
    "response": "Because now there are too many square miles of concrete and asphalt.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "Does that have something to do with the ruthlessness of the business?",
    "response": "No.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "Then was it because a lot of people realized they could make a fast buck here?",
    "response": "First of all, things happen in increments, right? They don't happen all at once. But people didn't start these companies just to make a buck. I mean they started businesses with very romantic notions. It wasn't just money. Nobody would say to himself, \"Jesus, I think next Monday my friend and I are going to start a company so we can make lots of money.\"",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "No, but you think you'd be the same person today if your aggregate wealth consisted of one Volkswagen van?",
    "response": "Obviously not. But that's sort of a meaningless question.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "No, what I'm suggesting is that some people started companies because they were fascinated by the technology and a lot of other people started companies because they thought they could make a buck.",
    "response": "Not the really great ones.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "Then what, if not money, defines the social pecking order out there?",
    "response": "A combination of having pioneered something significant, and having built a thriving organization. The right company, that's very important. In other words, even though some people have come out with neat products, if their company is perceived as a sweatshop or a revolving door, it's not considered much of a success. Remember, the role models were Hewlett and Packard. Their main achievement was that they built a company. Nobody remembers their first frequency-counter, their first audio oscillator, their first this or that. And they sell so many products now that no one person really symbolizes the company. But what does symbolize Hewlett-Packard is a revolutionary attitude toward people, a belief that people should be treated fairly, that the differentiation between labor and management should go away. And they built a company and they lived that philosophy for 35 or 40 years and that's why they're heroes. Hewlett and Packard started what became the Valley.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "What skill do you think you have that allowed you to succeed?",
    "response": "Well, you know, there were probably a lot of guys out there sitting in garages who thought, \"Hmmm, let's make a computer.\" Why did we succeed? I think we were very good at what we did and we surrounded ourselves by very fine people. See, one of the things you have to remember is that we started off with a very idealistic perspective—that doing something with the highest quality, doing it right the first time, would really be cheaper than having to go back and do it again. Ideas like that.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "Can you be more specific?",
    "response": "No, because that's as specific as you get. Just general feelings about things, without any experience to back them up.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "They're not based on, say, \"Gee, look what happened to Hewlett-Packard\"?",
    "response": "No, no, no. We just sort of had these feelings. We started to run the company our way and it turned out things we were doing worked. We never lost sight of how our idealism could translate into tangible results that were also acceptable in a more traditional sense.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "You seem to have postured Apple's image as the last crusade against the IBM-ization of the world.",
    "response": "You know, that's not quite right. If you froze technology today, it would be like freezing the automobile in 1915: you wouldn't have automatic transmissions, you wouldn't have electric starters. You don't want to see IBM freeze the standards.But the flip side of that is that this industry has matured more rapidly than any other industry in the history of business and there are suddenly things that billion-dollar class companies can do that $100 million or $10 million class companies can't do. For example, Apple will spend the better part of $100 million this year on research and development, and will spend the better part of $100 million on advertising. Now, IBM will spend that on personal computers alone. And if IBM and Apple invest that money wisely, it will be very difficult for the $10 million or even the $100 million class companies to keep up.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "Is there any company besides Apple and IBM that could keep up?",
    "response": "AT&T obviously could choose to invest $200 million. General Electric could obviously choose to invest $200 million. The question is will they? Will they take the risk? Do they see promise? Do they have the passion to innovate?",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "Out here there are traffic jams at 7:30 in the morning, even though people in the Valley have this reputation of being laid back...",
    "response": "Oh right, people work very hard here. And I think you have to differentiate between a true workaholic, and somebody who loves his work and wants to work because he gets true satisfaction and enjoyment out of it. The perfect example is the software people who don't get in until noon but they work until two in the morning. And they like it.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "Don't you ever wake up in the morning and say to yourself, \"There's no reason for me to work another day for the rest of my life. I've made enough money so that I can just have a good time, do anything I want...\"",
    "response": "Well yeah, I suppose some people say that. But the question ignores all the reasons why people do things here. The money is literally a 25 percent factor, at most. The journey is the reward. It's not just the accomplishment of something incredible. It's the actual doing of something incredible, day in and day out, getting the chance to participate in something really incredible. I mean that's the feeling we've had. I think everyone on the Mac team would have paid to come to work every day.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "I don't say this snidely, but that's a very easy thing for somebody to say who owns 6.9 million shares of Apple stock.",
    "response": "Then go ask the rest of them. Do you know how many places Burrell [Smith, Mac's hardware designer] and Andy [Hertzfeld, the operating-system designer] could go to tomorrow if they wanted to? Sure, they have a lot of money, and they could go work anywhere else they wanted to.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "But here you have a guy like Andy who spends I don't know how many thousands of dollars renovating his kitchen, and he never cooks a meal in it!",
    "response": "So what? What's the point?",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "Well, I'm talking about quality of life. One of the things that strikes me about Silicon Valley is that nobody seems to do anything but work.",
    "response": "A lot of people will probably take this analogy wrong, but there are a good number of people who would have loved to have had even the most menial job on the Manhattan Project in Los Alamos and watch those brilliant people work together for that period of time.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "There are also a lot of people who want to join the Marines.",
    "response": "No, no. There are moments in history which are significant and to be a part of those moments is an incredible experience. In other words, there are more important things than cooking in your own kitchen.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "I'm simply suggesting there's a very interesting relationship in this Valley between work, money and personal life.",
    "response": "Well, I don't know what this Valley is. I work at Apple. I'm there so many hours a day and I don't visit other places; I'm not an expert on Silicon Valley. What I do see is a small group of people who are artists and care more about their art than they do about almost anything else. It's more important than finding a girlfriend, it's more important... than cooking a meal, it's more important than joining the Marines, it's more important than whatever. Look at the way artists work. They're not typically the most \"balanced\" people in the world. Now, yes, we have a few workaholics here who are trying to escape other things, of course. But the majority of people out here have made very conscious decisions; they really have.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "How quickly did you become a millionaire?",
    "response": "When I was 23, I had a net worth of over a million dollars. At 24, it was over $10 million, and at 25, it was over $100 million.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "How did that affect the quality of your dates?",
    "response": "My dates? Nothing really changed, because I don't think about it that much. The people who think about those things a lot I never meet.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sometimes it's got to be overwhelming to you that about 10 years ago you were at some festival on the Ganges river and now you're running a billion-dollar corporation.",
    "response": "Yeah, well, OK. What do you want me to say? Give me the possible responses, I'll pick one.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "Well, I think there are an infinite number of responses. I'm simply suggesting that it somehow relates to Andy Hertzfeld never cooking a meal in his own kitchen.",
    "response": "I don't know what it relates to. Andy and I are roughly the same age, right? There's a whole set of things that neither of us has ever done before, you know: neither of us has ever been married before; neither of us has come home at 5 o'clock and hung out by the pool. I mean, there's a whole set of things. And we've chosen, at least in part, to spend a large number of hours and a large amount of our energy in a different way, making a computer.Now other people make things too. Other people put their energy into having a family, which I think is wonderful—I'd love to do it myself—or they put their energy into making a career or making this or making that.We've put our energy into making Macintosh over the last two years, which we thought would make a difference to a group of people that we wouldn't ever really know, but we'll walk into classrooms and see 50 Macintoshes and we'll feel good.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "When Apple was starting up, were people always conscious of stock options?",
    "response": "Oh sure. Well, not as much as they are now. Apple was the first company that gave stock options to almost everybody, every engineer, every middle-level marketing guy and so on.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "It strikes me that very few people cash in their chips here.",
    "response": "Some do and some don't. One of the trends I've seen is that once things seem a little stable, once the company has made it over some critical hurdles, some of the people will sell enough of their stock to buy a house or do something which may not mean that much to them, but will mean something, let's say, to their spouse or to their family, which hasn't seen enough of them for the last two years. They'll want to do something to sort of say, \"Hey, you know, what I've been working on really has been valuable, it really has been worth it and besides my loving it, it has produced something for the family or for both of us.\"",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "A lot of analysts and venture capitalists I've talked to think you're absolutely crazy to still have as much Apple stock as you have. Is it a matter of pride?",
    "response": "Well, it's a lot of things. Certainly, a year ago the stuff was worth, you know, more than twice as much as it's worth now. Last year, it decreased by about $200 million. I'm the only person I know that's lost a quarter of a billion dollars in one year.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does that make you feel?",
    "response": "It's very character building!",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1984 Access Magazine Interview"
  },
  {
    "question": "Was there a point at which Apple stopped being fun?",
    "response": "Well, Apple was about as pure of a Silicon Valley company as you could imagine. We started in a garage. Woz (co-founder Stephen Wozniak) and I both grew up in Silicon Valley. Our role model was Hewlett-Packard (the electronics company). And so I guess that's what we went into it thinking. Hewlett-Packard, you know, Jobs and Wozniak. And, as you recall, it was a very small company for a long time. But the industry started to grow very rapidly in the 1979-80 time frame. The Macintosh team was what is commonly known now as intrapreneurship—only a few years before the term was coined—a group of people going in essence back to the garage, but in a large company. But again, that was a core team of 50 people. So that attracted a lot of people that really did want to work at a small company, in a way.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "But were things generally going as you wanted them to for Apple and for Steve Jobs?",
    "response": "Well, if I look at myself and ask, \"What am I best at and what do I enjoy most doing?\" I think what I'm best at is creating sort of new innovative products. That's what I enjoy doing. I enjoy, and I'm best working with, a small team of talented people. That's what I did with the Apple II, and that's what I did with the Macintosh.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Once John Sculley came in and took over, how did your role change? Was there somepoint when you thought, \"I'm not having a lot of fun running this giant corporation?\"",
    "response": "I was very happy in the early days of Macintosh. Really, up until very near the end. I don't think that my role in life is to run big organizations and do incremental improvements. Well, you know, I think that John felt that after the reorganization, it was important for me to not be at Apple for him to accomplish what he wanted to accomplish. And, as you know, he issued that public statement that there was no role for me there then or in the future, or in the foreseeable future. And that was about as black-and-white as you need to make things. Probably a little more black-and-white than it needed to be. And I, you know, I respect his right to make that decision.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "How did you react when you heard the board's decision? These were people that you knew and worked with for a long time.",
    "response": "Oh, yeah. I mean in my wildest imagination, I couldn't have come up with such a wild ending to all of this. I had hoped that my life would take on the quality of an interesting tapestry where I would have weaved in and out of Apple: I would have been there a period of time, and maybe I would have gone off and done something else to contribute, but connected with Apple, and then maybe come back and stay for a lengthy time period and then go off and do something else. But it's just not going to work out that way. So I had 10 of the best years of my life, you know. And I don't regret much of anything.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Is there an inevitable break between being an entrepreneur and a businessman? Arethe people who get things going different?",
    "response": "I don't know. You look back at the personal-computer industry, IBM and DEC and Hewlett-Packard weren't the people that invented the personal computer. It took a bunch of rambunctious upstarts, working with very little resources but a certain amount of vision and commitment, to do it. And Apple has clearly now joined that status and the ranks of those other companies. It probably is true that the people who have been able to come up with the innovations in many industries are maybe not the people that either are best skilled at, or, frankly, enjoy running a large enterprise where they lose contact with the day-to-day workings of that innovative process. Dr. Land at Polaroid, he's a perfect example.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "That leads to the next question. . .",
    "response": "And in 10 years will I be faced with the same dilemma again? Maybe, maybe I will.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Have you set aside in your own mind any desire to do another Apple?",
    "response": "Oh, yeah. Absolutely. I helped shepherd Apple from a garage to a billion-and-a-half-dollar company. I'm probably not the best person in the world to shepherd it to a five- or ten-billion-dollar company, which I think is probably its destiny. And so I haven't got any sort of odd chip on my shoulder about proving anything to myself or anybody else. And remember, though the outside world looks at success from a numerical point of view, my yardstick might be quite different than that. My yardstick may be how every computer that's designed from here on out will have to be at least as good as a Macintosh.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Are you saying in there that you could have run the giant Apple?",
    "response": "If I had felt that I was the person to run Apple in 1983, then I would have thrown my own name into the hat for the job, which I did not. So it was a conscious decision on my part to find John Sculley.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Were you surprised how that all turned out?",
    "response": "If my vote had counted for everything at Apple, I certainly would not have told Steve Jobs that there was no place for him at Apple. But my vote was just one vote. So...",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the end it did get down to who would run the company.",
    "response": "I think, more importantly, it was which philosophy and perspective, more than an individual person. You know, my philosophy is—it's always been very simple. And it has its flaws, which I'll go into. My philosophy is that everything starts with a great product. So, you know, I obviously believed in listening to customers, but customers can't tell you about the next breakthrough that's going to happen next year that's going to change the whole industry. So you have to listen very carefully. But then you have to go and sort of stow away—you have to go hide away with people that really understand the technology, but also really care about the customers, and dream up this next breakthrough. And that's my perspective, that everything starts with a great product. And that has its flaws. Ihave certainly been accused of not listening to the customers enough. And I think there is probably a certain amount of that that's valid.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Can you describe a little bit your role at Apple after the reorganization?",
    "response": "My calendar had some commitments on it that obviously were slightly more long-term than I could adjust immediately. Those included a trip to the Soviet Union; it included a trip to introduce the Macintosh office products in Europe. Given the state of mind I was in, I think I did a pretty good job for the company with that. But I was, you know, asked to move out of my office. They leased a little building across the street from most of the other Apple buildings. I, we nicknamed it Siberia.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "How were you told about that?",
    "response": "My associate was told about it. Yeah, she said, \"They want you to get out in two weeks.\"",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "How did you feel?",
    "response": "Well, given the background of the other feelings I was feeling at the time, this was nothing out of the ordinary. So I moved across the street, and I made sure that all of the executive staff had my home phone number. I knew that John had it, and I called the rest of them personally and made sure they had it and told them that I wanted to be useful in any way i could, and to please call me if I could help on anything. And they all had a, you know, a cordial phrase, but none of them ever called back. And so I used to go into work, I'd get there and I would have one or two phone calls to perform, a little bit of mail to look at. But ... this was in June, July ... most of the corporate-management reports stopped flowing by my desk. A few people might see my car in the parking lot and come over and commiserate. And I would get depressed and go home in three or four hours, really depressed. I did that a few times and I decided that was mentally unhealthy. So I just stopped going in. You know, there was nobody really there to miss me.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Do you feel that they have taken your company away from you?",
    "response": "To me, Apple exists in the spirit of the people that work there, and the sort of philosophies and purpose by which they go about their business. So if Apple just becomes a place where computers are a commodity item and where the romance is gone, and where people forget that computers are the most incredible invention that man has ever invented, then I'll feel I have lost Apple. But if I'm a million miles away and all those people still feel those things and they're still working to make the next great personal computer, then I will feel that my genes are still in there.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Does it still have that spirit now?",
    "response": "Well, I think you got a good ... I'm not the one to ask that. You're putting me in a tough spot.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "When you were going into Apple during the summer, were you already thinking about alternatives?",
    "response": "No.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "You still thought there was a chance they'd make an R&D group for Steve to run?",
    "response": "The hardest, one of the five most difficult days was that day John said at the analysts meeting about there not being a role for me in the future, and he said it again in another analysts meeting a week later. He didn't say it to me directly, he said it to the press. You've probably had somebody punch you in the stomach and it knocks the wind out of you and you can't breathe. If you relax you'll start breathing again. That's how I felt all summer long. The thing I had to do was try to relax. It was hard. But I went for a lot of long walks in the woods and didn't really talk to a lot of people.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why don't you tell us some of the details of how this new thing came together?",
    "response": "The interesting thing about the group is that we've all known each other for four years. And we have an immense amount of confidence in each others' abilities and genuinely like each other. And all have a desire to have a small company where we can influence its destiny and have a really fun place to work. We talked about this enterprise, you know, for the first time less than two weeks before I told the board that I wanted to start this company. And we have no business plan. We haven't done anything. Now, you might say we're all crazy. We have a general direction. We want to find out what higher education needs. We plan to go visit a lot of colleges in October and just listen. Then we want to build it for them, whatever it is. Courseware, whatever.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "You've talked about being tough to get along with, having a rough-edge personality. Did you contribute in some way to your own downfall?",
    "response": "You know, I'm not a 62-year-old statesman that's traveled around the world all his life. So I'm sure that there was a situation when I was 25 that if I could go back, knowing what I know now, I could have handled much better. And I'm sure I'll be able to say the same thing when I'm 35 about the situation in 1985. I can be very intense in my convictions. And I don't know; all in all, I kind of like myself and I'm not that anxious to change.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "But has this experience changed you?",
    "response": "Oh, this has—yeah, I think I am growing from this, and I think I'm learning a lot from it. I'm not sure how or what yet. But yes, I feel that way. (But) I'm not bitter. I'm not bitter.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Can you talk a little about how your relationship with John Sculley has changed?",
    "response": "Well, given the fact that I've spoken to him only three times since (May)—that says something about the degree of communication we've had—I don't know what will happen with my relationship with John.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "What did you learn from it so far?",
    "response": "If John Sculley calls me on the phone, I'll answer it.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "We wanted to talk about you personally.",
    "response": "What have we been talking about?",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "We mean apart from Apple.",
    "response": "Oh.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "There's been a lot in the press about your interest in Buddhism, vegetarianism.",
    "response": "As we descend into the isms.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "The isms. Are you still interested in those things?",
    "response": "Well, I don't know what to say. I mean I don't eat meat, and I don't go to church every Sunday.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "They said at some point you had thought of going to Japan and sitting in a monastery.",
    "response": "Yeah, yeah. I'm glad I didn't do that. I know this is going to sound really, really corny. But I feel like I'm an American, and I was born here. And the fate of the world is in America's hands right now. I really feel that. And you know I'm going to live my life here and do what I can to help.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "A lot of people, given your sort of iconic existence, think about politics.",
    "response": "Well, I have thought about it some. People from both parties have called and chatted about it. But now I think the best use that society can put me to is to really do what I know how to do. I've got too much hair left for politics.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Now that you're 30 and an estate owner, do you see a settled life for yourself, a family, big Silicon Valley parties, furniture?",
    "response": "Actually, I bought a few Eames chairs so I have a place to sit down and read a book, other than the floor. No, I gotta tell you, the thing I want to do more than anything now is get to work. I, we've got to go rent a building, we've got to decide on a name, we've got to file incorporation papers. It sounds like drudgery, but I long for it right now. So yeah, I'd like to have some kids one day. But...",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Have you seen Silicon Valley change, other than in its property values?",
    "response": "Sure it's changed. First of all, the valley has gotten to be a much larger place, it's contributing quite a bit now to the gross national product. And the entrepreneurship has gotten much more sophisticated. I mean if you want to start a company now, there are companies that help you start a company. What I hope they don't get stuck on is thinking that Apple is the yardstick of success. Silicon Valley still is a mecca that attracts amazing amounts of technical talent and I'm real excited about the next 10 years. Software is what will distinguish products in the next 10 years. And I think the technology for software is just starting to come into its own.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Are some of the nice things about the valley gone for good?",
    "response": "Hewlett and Packard, the first generation, handed over leadership to the second; they made a smooth transition. But it's not Bill Hewlett and Dave Packard there. Intel is partially owned by IBM. Rolm has been merged into IBM. So you have people that have a very different culture now who help to run some of the companies in the valley. I think it is fair to say that the people running Apple are not from the valley at this point in time. I think that some of that is inevitable. I honestly don't know what it is going to mean. If the culture of the valley and some of the principles and practices of the valley are truncated, then I think it is pretty likely that the innovation will stop.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Might Apple executives be worried that in a year from now your departure will be an embarrassment? You may have built an incredible new work station and it's going to be so terrific and so cheap that the shareholders will say, \"What, you let him do that?\" Could that be in the back of their minds?",
    "response": "I wasn't aware that Apple owned me, you know. I don't think they do. I think that I own me. And for me not to be able to practice my craft ever again in my life seems odd. We're not going to take any technology, any proprietary ideas out of Apple. We're willing to put that in writing. It is the law, anyway. There is nothing, by the way, that says Apple can't compete with us if they think what we're doing is such a great idea. It is hard to think that a $2 billion company with 4,300-plus people couldn't compete with six people in blue jeans.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "We survived 1984, and computers did not take over the world, though some people might find that hard to believe. If there's any one individual who can be either blamed or praised for the proliferation of computers, you, the 29-year-old father of the computer revolution, are the prime contender. It has also made you wealthy beyond dreams—your stock was worth almost a half billion dollars at one point, wasn't it?",
    "response": "I actually lost $250,000,000 in one year when the stock went down. [Laughs]",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "You can laugh about it?",
    "response": "I'm not going to let it ruin my life. Isn't it kind of funny? You know, my main reaction to this money thing is that it's humorous, all the attention to it, because it's hardly the most insightful or valuable thing that's happened to me in the past ten years. But it makes me feel old, sometimes, when I speak at a campus and I find that what students are most in awe of is the fact that I'm a millionaire. When I went to school, it was right after the Sixties and before this general wave of practical purposefulness had set in. Now students aren't even thinking in idealistic terms, or at least nowhere near as much. They certainly are not letting any of the philosophical issues of the day take up too much of their time as they study their business majors. The idealistic wind of the Sixties was still at our backs, though, and most of the people I know who are my age have that ingrained in them forever.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "It's interesting that the computer field has made millionaires of——",
    "response": "Young maniacs, I know.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "We were going to say guys like you and Steve Wozniak, working out of a garage only ten years ago. Just what is this revolution you two seem to have started?",
    "response": "We're living in the wake of the petrochemical revolution of 100 years ago. The petrochemical revolution gave us free energy—free mechanical energy, in this case. It changed the texture of society in most ways. This revolution, the information revolution, is a revolution of free energy as well, but of another kind: free intellectual energy. It's very crude today, yet our Macintosh computer takes less power than a 100-watt light bulb to run and it can save you hours a day. What will it be able to do ten or 20 years from now, or 50 years from now? This revolution will dwarf the petrochemical revolution. We're on the forefront.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Maybe we should pause and get your definition of what a computer is. How do they work?",
    "response": "Computers are actually pretty simple. We're sitting here on a bench in this cafe [for this part of the Interview]. Let's assume that you understood only the most rudimentary of directions and you asked how to find the rest room. I would have to describe it to you in very specific and precise instructions. I might say, \"Scoot sideways two meters off the bench. Stand erect. Lift left foot. Bend left knee until it is horizontal. Extend left foot and shift weight 300 centimeters forward ...\" and on and on. If you could interpret all those instructions 100 times faster than any other person in this cafe, you would appear to be a magician: You could run over and grab a milk shake and bring it back and set it on the table and snap your fingers, and I'd think you made the milk shake appear, because it was so fast relative to my perception. That's exactly what a computer does. It takes these very, very simple-minded instructions—\"Go fetch a number, add it to this number, put the result there, perceive if it's greater than this other number\"—but executes them at a rate of, let's say, 1,000,000 per second. At 1,000,000 per second, the results appear to be magic. That's a simple explanation, and the point is that people really don't have to understand how computers work. Most people have no concept of how an automatic transmission works, yet they know how to drive a car. You don't have to study physics to understand the laws of motion to drive a car. You don't have to understand any of this stuff to use Macintosh—but you asked [laughs].",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Obviously, you believe that computers are going to change our personal lives, but how would you persuade a skeptic? A holdout?",
    "response": "A computer is the most incredible tool we've ever seen. It can be a writing tool, a communications center, a supercalculator, a planner, a filer and an artistic instrument all in one, just by being given new instructions, or software, to work from. There are no other tools that have the power and versatility of a computer. We have no idea how far it's going to go. Right now, computers make our lives easier. They do work for us in fractions of a second that would take us hours. They increase the quality of life, some of that by simply automating drudgery and some of that by broadening our possibilities. As things progress, they'll be doing more and more for us.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "How about some concrete reasons to buy a computer today? An executive in your industry recently said, \"We've given people computers, but we haven't shown them what to do with them. I can balance my checkbook faster by hand than on my computer.\" Why should a person buy a computer?",
    "response": "There are different answers for different people. In business, that question is easy to answer: You really can prepare documents much faster and at a higher quality level, and you can do many things to increase office productivity. A computer frees people from much of the menial work. Besides that, you are giving them a tool that encourages them to be creative. Remember, computers are tools. Tools help us do our work better. In education, computers are the first thing to come along since books that will sit there and interact with you endlessly, without judgment. Socratic education isn't available anymore, and computers have the potential to be a real breakthrough in the educational process when used in conjunction with enlightened teachers. We're in most schools already.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Those are arguments for computers in business and in schools, but what about the home?",
    "response": "So far, that's more of a conceptual market than a real market. The primary reasons to buy a computer for your home now are that you want to do some business work at home or you want to run educational software for yourself or your children. If you can't justify buying a computer for one of those two reasons, the only other possible reason is that you just want to be computer literate. You know there's something going on, you don't exactly know what it is, so you want to learn. This will change: Computers will be essential in most homes.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What will change?",
    "response": "The most compelling reason for most people to buy a computer for the home will be to link it into a nationwide communications network. We're just in the beginning stages of what will be a truly remarkable breakthrough for most people—as remarkable as the telephone.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Specifically, what kind of breakthrough are you talking about?",
    "response": "I can only begin to speculate. We see that a lot in our industry: You don't know exactly what's going to result, but you know it's something very big and very good.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Then for now, aren't you asking home-computer buyers to invest $3000 in what is essentially an act of faith?",
    "response": "In the future, it won't be an act of faith. The hard part of what we're up against now is that people ask you about specifics and you can't tell them. A hundred years ago, if somebody had asked Alexander Graham Bell, \"What are you going to be able to do with a telephone?\" he wouldn't have been able to tell him the ways the telephone would affect the world. He didn't know that people would use the telephone to call up and find out what movies were playing that night or to order some groceries or call a relative on the other side of the globe. But remember that first the public telegraph was inaugurated, in 1844. It was an amazing breakthrough in communications. You could actually send messages from New York to San Francisco in an afternoon. People talked about putting a telegraph on every desk in America to improve productivity. But it wouldn't have worked. It required that people learn this whole sequence of strange incantations, Morse code, dots and dashes, to use the telegraph. It took about 40 hours to learn. The majority of people would never learn how to use it. So, fortunately, in the 1870s, Bell filed the patents for the telephone. It performed basically the same function as the telegraph, but people already knew how to use it. Also, the neatest thing about it was that besides allowing you to communicate with just words, it allowed you to sing.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Meaning what?",
    "response": "It allowed you to intone your words with meaning beyond the simple linguistics. And we're in the same situation today. Some people are saying that we ought to put an IBM PC on every desk in America to improve productivity. It won't work. The special incantations you have to learn this time are \"slash q-zs\" and things like that. The manual for WordStar, the most popular word-processing program, is 400 pages thick. To write a novel, you have to read a novel—one that reads like a mystery to most people. They're not going to learn slash q-z any more than they're going to learn Morse code. That is what Macintosh is all about. It's the first \"telephone\" of our industry. And, besides that, the neatest thing about it, to me, is that the Macintosh lets you sing the way the telephone did. You don't simply communicate words, you have special print styles and the ability to draw and add pictures to express yourself.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Is that really significant or is it simply a novelty? The Macintosh has been called \"the world's most expensive Etch A Sketch\" by at least one critic.",
    "response": "It's as significant as the difference between the telephone and the telegraph. Imagine what you could have done if you had this sophisticated an Etch A Sketch when you were growing up. But that's only a small part of it. Not only can it help you increase your productivity and your creativity enormously, but it also allows us to communicate more efficiently by using pictures and graphs as well as words and numbers.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Most computers use key strokes to enter instructions, but Macintosh replaces many of them with something called a mouse—a little box that is rolled around on your desk and guides a pointer on your computer screen. It's a big change for people used to keyboards. Why the mouse?",
    "response": "If I want to tell you there is a spot on your shirt, I'm not going to do it linguistically: \"There's a spot on your shirt 14 centimeters down from the collar and three centimeters to the left of your button.\" If you have a spot—\"There!\" [He points]—I'll point to it. Pointing is a metaphor we all know. We've done a lot of studies and tests on that, and it's much faster to do all kinds of functions, such as cutting and pasting, with a mouse, so it's not only easier to use but more efficient.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "How long did it take to develop Macintosh?",
    "response": "It was more than two years on the computer itself. We had been working on the technology behind it for years before that. I don't think I've ever worked so hard on something, but working on Macintosh was the neatest experience of my life. Almost everyone who worked on it will say that. None of us wanted to release it at the end. It was as though we knew that once it was out of our hands, it wouldn't be ours anymore. When we finally presented it at the shareholders' meeting, everyone in the auditorium stood up and gave it a five-minute ovation. What was incredible to me was that I could see the Mac team in the first few rows. It was as though none of us could believe that we'd actually finished it. Everyone started crying.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "We were warned about you: Before this Interview began, someone said we were \"about to be snowed by the best.\"",
    "response": "[Smiling] We're just enthusiastic about what we do.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "But considering that enthusiasm, the multimillion-dollar ad campaigns and your own ability to get press coverage, how does the consumer know what's behind the hype?",
    "response": "Ad campaigns are necessary for competition; IBM's ads are everywhere. But good PR educates people; that's all it is. You can't con people in this business. The products speak for themselves.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Aside from some of the recurrent criticisms—that the mouse is inefficient, that the Macintosh screen is only black and white—the most serious charge is that Apple overprices its products. Do you care to answer any or all?",
    "response": "We've done studies that prove that the mouse is faster than traditional ways of moving through data or applications. Someday we may be able to build a color screen for a reasonable price. As to overpricing, the start-up of a new product makes it more expensive than it will be later. The more we can produce, the lower the price will get——",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "That's what critics charge you with: hooking the enthusiasts with premium prices, then turning around and lowering your prices to catch the rest of the market.",
    "response": "That's simply untrue. As soon as we can lower prices, we do. It's true that our computers are less expensive today than they were a few years ago, or even last year. But that's also true of the IBM PC. Our goal is to get computers out to tens of millions of people, and the cheaper we can make them, the easier it's going to be to do that. I'd love it if Macintosh cost $1000.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "How about people who bought Lisa and Apple III, the two computers you released prior to Macintosh? You've left them with incompatible, out-of-date products.",
    "response": "If you want to try that one, add the people who bought the IBM PCs or the PCjrs to that list, too. As far as Lisa is concerned, since some of its technology was used in the Macintosh, it can now run Macintosh software and is being seen as a big brother to Macintosh; though it was unsuccessful at first, our sales of Lisa are going through the roof. We're also still selling more than 2000 Apple IIIs a month—more than half to repeat buyers. The over-all point is that new technology will not necessarily replace old technology, but it will date it. By definition. Eventually, it will replace it. But it's like people who had black-and-white TVs when color came out. They eventually decided whether or not the new technology was worth the investment.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "At the rate things are changing, won't Mac itself be out of date within a few years?",
    "response": "Before Macintosh, there were two standards: Apple II and IBM PC. Those two standards are like rivers carved in the rock bed of a canyon. It's taken years to carve them—seven years to carve the Apple II and four years to carve the IBM. What we have done with Macintosh is that in less than a year, through the momentum of the revolutionary aspects of the product and through every ounce of marketing that we have as a company, we have been able to blast a third channel through that rock and make a third river, a third standard. In my opinion, there are only two companies that can do that today, Apple and IBM. Maybe that's too bad, but to do it right now is just a monumental effort, and I don't think that Apple or IBM will do that in the next three or four years. Toward the end of the Eighties, we may be seeing some new things.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "And in the meantime?",
    "response": "The developments will be in making the products more and more portable, networking them, getting out laser printers, getting out shared data bases, getting out more communications ability, maybe the merging of the telephone and the personal computer.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "You have a lot riding on this one. Some people have said that Macintosh will make or break Apple. After Lisa and Apple III, Apple stock plummeted and the industry speculated that Apple might not survive.",
    "response": "Yeah, we felt the weight of the world on our shoulders. We knew that we had to pull the rabbit out of the hat with Macintosh, or else we'd never realize the dreams we had for either the products or the company.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "How serious was it? Was Apple near bankruptcy?",
    "response": "No, no, no. In fact, 1983, when all these predictions were being made, was a phenomenally successful year for Apple. We virtually doubled in size in 1983. We went from $583,000,000 in 1982 to something like $980,000,000 in sales. It was almost all Apple II-related. It just didn't live up to our expectations. If Macintosh weren't a success, we probably would have stayed at something like a billion dollars a year, selling Apple IIs and versions of it.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Then what was behind the talk last year that Apple had had it?",
    "response": "IBM was coming on very, very strong, and the momentum was switching to IBM. The software developers were moving to IBM. The dealers were talking more and more of IBM. It became clear to all of us who worked on Macintosh that it was just gonna blow the socks off the industry, that it was going to redefine the industry. And that's exactly what it had to do. If Macintosh hadn't been successful, then I should have just thrown in the towel, because my vision of the whole industry would have been totally wrong.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Apple III was supposed to have been your souped-up Apple II, but it has been a failure since it was launched, four years ago. You recalled the first 14,000, and even the revised Apple III never took off. How much was lost on Apple III?",
    "response": "Infinite, incalculable amounts. I think if the III had been more successful, IBM would have had a much harder time entering the market place. But that's life. I think we emerged from that experience much stronger.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Yet when Lisa came out, it, too, was a relative failure in the market place. What went wrong?",
    "response": "First of all, it was too expensive—about ten grand. We had gotten Fortune 500-itis, trying to sell to those huge corporations, when our roots were selling to people. There were other problems: late shipping; the software didn't come together in the end as well as we hoped and we lost a lot of momentum. And IBM's coming on very strong, coupled with our being about six months late, coupled with the price's being too high, plus another strategic mistake we made—deciding to sell Lisa only through about 150 dealers, which was absolutely foolish on our part—meant it was a very costly mistake. We decided to hire people we thought were marketing and management experts. Not a bad idea, but unfortunately, this was such a new business that the things the so-called professionals knew were almost detriments to their success in this new way of looking at business.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Was that a reflection of insecurity on your part—\"This thing has gotten big and now we're playing hardball; I better bring in some real pros\"?",
    "response": "Remember, we were 23, 24 and 25 years old. We had never done any of this before, so it seemed like a good thing to do.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Were most of those decisions, good and bad, yours?",
    "response": "We tried never to have one person make all the decisions. There were three people running the company at that time: Mike Scott, Mike Markkula and myself. Now it's John Sculley [Apple's president] and myself. In the early days, if there was a disagreement, I would generally defer my judgment to some of the other people who had more experience than I had. In many cases, they were right. In some important cases, if we had gone my way, we would have done better.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "You wanted to run the Lisa division. Markkula and Scott, who were, in effect, your bosses, even though you had a hand in hiring them, didn't feel you were capable, right?",
    "response": "After setting up the framework for the concepts and finding the key people and sort of setting the technical directions, Scotty decided I didn't have the experience to run the thing. It hurt a lot. There's no getting around it.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Did you feel you were losing Apple?",
    "response": "There was a bit of that, I guess, but the thing that was harder for me was that they hired a lot of people in the Lisa group who didn't share the vision we originally had. There was a big conflict in the Lisa group between the people who wanted, in essence, to build something like Macintosh and the people hired from Hewlett-Packard and other companies who brought with them a perspective of larger machines, corporate sales. I just decided that I was going to go off and do that myself with a small group, sort of go back to the garage, to design the Macintosh. They didn't take us very seriously. I think Scotty was just sort of humoring me.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "But this was the company that you founded. Weren't you resentful?",
    "response": "You can never resent your kid.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Even when your kid tells you to fuck off?",
    "response": "I wouldn't feel resentment. I'd feel great sorrow about it and I'd be frustrated, which I was. But I got the best people who were at Apple, because I thought that if we didn't do that, we'd be in real trouble. Of course, it was those people who came up with Macintosh. [Shrugs] Look at Mac.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "That verdict is far from in. In fact, you ushered in the Mac with a lot of the same fanfare that preceded the Lisa, and the Lisa failed initially.",
    "response": "It's true: We expressed very high hopes for Lisa and we were wrong. The hardest thing for us was that we knew Macintosh was coming, and Macintosh seemed to overcome every possible objection to Lisa. As a company, we would be getting back to our roots—selling computers to people, not corporations. We went off and built the most insanely great computer in the world.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Does it take insane people to make insanely great things?",
    "response": "Actually, making an insanely great product has a lot to do with the process of making the product, how you learn things and adopt new ideas and throw out old ideas. But, yeah, the people who made Mac are sort of on the edge.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What's the difference between the people who have insanely great ideas and the people who pull off those insanely great ideas?",
    "response": "Let me compare it with IBM. How come the Mac group produced Mac and the people at IBM produced the PCjr? We think the Mac will sell zillions, but we didn't build Mac for anybody else. We built it for ourselves. We were the group of people who were going to judge whether it was great or not. We weren't going to go out and do market research. We just wanted to build the best thing we could build. When you're a carpenter making a beautiful chest of drawers, you're not going to use a piece of plywood on the back, even though it faces the wall and nobody will ever see it. You'll know it's there, so you're going to use a beautiful piece of wood on the back. For you to sleep well at night, the aesthetic, the quality, has to be carried all the way through.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Are you saying that the people who made the PCjr don't have that kind of pride in the product?",
    "response": "If they did, they wouldn't have turned out the PCjr. It seems clear to me that they were designing that on the basis of market research for a specific market segment, for a specific demographic type of customer, and they hoped that if they built this, lots of people would buy them and they'd make lots of money. Those are different motivations. The people in the Mac group wanted to build the greatest computer that has ever been seen.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why is the computer field dominated by people so young? The average age of Apple employees is 29.",
    "response": "It's often the same with any new, revolutionary thing. People get stuck as they get older. Our minds are sort of electrochemical computers. Your thoughts construct patterns like scaffolding in your mind. You are really etching chemical patterns. In most cases, people get stuck in those patterns, just like grooves in a record, and they never get out of them. It's a rare person who etches grooves that are other than a specific way of looking at things, a specific way of questioning things. It's rare that you see an artist in his 30s or 40s able to really contribute something amazing. Of course, there are some people who are innately curious, forever little kids in their awe of life, but they're rare.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "A lot of guys in their 40s are going to be real pleased with you. Let's move on to the other thing that people talk about when they mention Apple—the company, not the computer. You feel a similar sense of mission about the way things are run at Apple, don't you?",
    "response": "I do feel there is another way we have an effect on society besides our computers. I think Apple has a chance to be the model of a Fortune 500 company in the late Eighties and early Nineties. Ten to 15 years ago, if you asked people to make a list of the five most exciting companies in America, Polaroid and Xerox would have been on everyone's list. Where are they now? They would be on no one's list today. What happened? Companies, as they grow to become multibillion-dollar entities, somehow lose their vision. They insert lots of layers of middle management between the people running the company and the people doing the work. They no longer have an inherent feel or a passion about the products. The creative people, who are the ones who care passionately, have to persuade five layers of management to do what they know is the right thing to do.What happens in most companies is that you don't keep great people under working environments where individual accomplishment is discouraged rather than encouraged. The great people leave and you end up with mediocrity. I know, because that's how Apple was built. Apple is an Ellis Island company. Apple is built on refugees from other companies. These are the extremely bright individual contributors who were troublemakers at other companies.\nYou know, Dr. Edwin Land was a troublemaker. He dropped out of Harvard and founded Polaroid. Not only was he one of the great inventors of our time but, more important, he saw the intersection of art and science and business and built an organization to reflect that. Polaroid did that for some years, but eventually Dr. Land, one of those brilliant troublemakers, was asked to leave his own company—which is one of the dumbest things I've ever heard of. So Land, at 75, went off to spend the remainder of his life doing pure science, trying to crack the code of color vision. The man is a national treasure. I don't understand why people like that can't be held up as models: This is the most incredible thing to be—not an astronaut, not a football player—but this.\nAnyway, one of our biggest challenges, and the one I think John Sculley and I should be judged on in five to ten years, is making Apple an incredibly great ten- or 20-billion-dollar company. Will it still have the spirit it does today? We're charting new territory. There are no models that we can look to for our high growth, for some of the new management concepts we have. So we're having to find our own way.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "If Apple is really that kind of company, then why the projected twenty-fold growth? Why not stay relatively small?",
    "response": "The way it's going to work out is that in our business, in order to continue to be one of the major contributors, we're going to have to be a ten-billion-dollar company. That growth is required for us to keep up with the competition. Our concern is how we become that, rather than the dollar goal, which is meaningless to us.\nAt Apple, people are putting in 18-hour days. We attract a different type of person—a person who doesn't want to wait five or ten years to have someone take a giant risk on him or her. Someone who really wants to get in a little over his head and make a little dent in the universe. We are aware that we are doing something significant. We're here at the beginning of it and we're able to shape how it goes. Everyone here has the sense that right now is one of those moments when we are influencing the future. Most of the time, we're taking things. Neither you nor I made the clothes we wear; we don't make the food or grow the foods we eat; we use a language that was developed by other people; we use another society's mathematics. Very rarely do we get a chance to put something back into that pool. I think we have that opportunity now. And no, we don't know where it will lead. We just know there's something much bigger than any of us here.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "You've said that the business market is crucial for you to conquer with Macintosh. Can you beat IBM at work?",
    "response": "Yes. The business market has several sectors. Rather than just thinking of the Fortune 500, which is where IBM is strongest, I like to think of the Fortune 5,000,000 or 14,000,000. There are 14,000,000 small businesses in this country. I think that the vast group of people who need to be computerized includes that large number of medium and small businesses. We're going to try to be able to bring some meaningful solutions to them in 1985.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "How?",
    "response": "Our approach is to think of them not as businesses but as collections of people. We want to qualitatively change the way people work. We don't just want to help them do word processing faster or add numbers faster. We want to change the way they can communicate with one another. We're seeing five-page memos get compressed to one-page memos because we can use a picture to express the key concept. We're seeing less paper flying around and more quality of communication. And it's more fun. There's always been this myth that really neat, fun people at home all of a sudden have to become very dull and boring when they come to work. It's simply not true. If we can inject that liberal-arts spirit into the very serious realm of business, I think it will be a worthwhile contribution. We can't even conceive of how far it will go.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "But in the business market, you're fighting the IBM name as much as anything. People associate IBM with stability and efficiency. The new entry in the computer field, A.T.&T., has that one up on you, too. Apple is a relatively young and untested company, particularly in the eyes of corporations that might be customers.",
    "response": "It's Macintosh's job to really penetrate the business market place. IBM focuses on the top down, the mainframe centric approach to selling in businesses. If we are going to be successful, we've got to approach this from a grass-roots point of view. To use networking as an example, rather than focusing on wiring up whole companies, as IBM is doing, we're going to focus on the phenomenon of the small work group.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "One of the experts in the field says that for this industry to really flourish, and for it to benefit the consumer, one standard has to prevail.",
    "response": "That's simply untrue. Insisting that we need one standard now is like saying that they needed one standard for automobiles in 1920. There would have been no innovations such as the automatic transmission, power steering and independent suspension if they believed that. The last thing we want to do is freeze technology. With computers, Macintosh is revolutionary. There is no question that Macintosh's technology is superior to IBM's. There is a clear need for an alternative to IBM.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Was any of your decision not to become compatible with IBM based on the fact that you didn't want to knuckle under to IBM? One critic says that the reason Mac isn't IBM-compatible is mere arrogance—that \"Steve Jobs was saying 'Fuck you' to IBM.\"",
    "response": "It wasn't that we had to express our manhood by being different, no.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Then why were you?",
    "response": "The main thing is very simply that the technology we developed is superior. It could not be this good if we became compatible with IBM. Of course, it's true that we don't want IBM to dominate this industry. A lot of people thought we were nuts for not being IBM-compatible, for not living under IBM's umbrella. There were two key reasons we chose to bet our company on not doing that: The first was that we thought—and I think as history is unfolding, we're being proved correct—that IBM would fold its umbrella on the companies making compatible computers and absolutely crush them.\nSecond and more important, we did not go IBM-compatible because of the product vision that drives this company. We think that computers are the most remarkable tools that humankind has ever come up with, and we think that people are basically tool users. So if we can just get lots of computers to lots of people, it will make some qualitative difference in the world. What we want to do at Apple is make computers into appliances and get them to tens of millions of people. That's simply what we want to do. And we couldn't do that with the current IBM-generation type of technology. So we had to do something different. That's why we came up with the Macintosh.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "From 1981 to 1983, your share of the personal-computer sales slipped from 29 percent to 23 percent. IBM's part has grown from three percent to 28 percent in the same time. How do you fight the numbers?",
    "response": "We've never worried about numbers. In the market place, Apple is trying to focus the spotlight on products, because products really make a difference. IBM is trying to focus the spotlight on service, support, security, mainframes and motherhood. Now, Apple's key observation three years ago was that when you're shipping 10,000,000 computers a year, even IBM does not have enough mothers to ship one with every computer. So you've got to build motherhood into the computer. And that's a big part of what Macintosh is all about. All these things show that it really is coming down to just Apple and IBM. If, for some reason, we make some giant mistakes and IBM wins, my personal feeling is that we are going to enter sort of a computer Dark Ages for about 20 years. Once IBM gains control of a market sector, they almost always stop innovation. They prevent innovation from happening.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why?",
    "response": "Look at this example: Frito-Lay is a very interesting company. They call on more than half a million accounts a week. There's a Frito-Lay rack in each store, and the chips are all there, and every store's got the identical rack and the big ones have multiples. For Frito-Lay, the biggest problem is stale product—bad chips, so to speak. For Frito-Lay's service, they've got, like, 10,000 guys who run around and take out the stale product and replace it with good product. They talk to the manager of that department and they make sure everything's fine. Because of that service and support, they now have more than an 80 percent share of every segment of chips that they're in. Nobody else can break into that. As long as they keep doing what they do well, nobody else can get 80 percent of the market share, because they can't get the sales and support staff. They can't get it because they can't afford it. They can't afford it because they don't have 80 percent of the market share. It's catch-22. Nobody will ever be able to break into their franchise. Frito-Lay doesn't have to innovate very much. They just watch all the little chip companies come out with something new, study it for a year, and a year or two years later they come out with their own, service and support it to death, and they've got 80 percent of the market share of the new product a year later.\nIBM is playing exactly the same game. If you look at the mainframe market place, there's been virtually zero innovation since IBM got dominant control of that market place 15 years ago. They are going to do the same thing in every other sector of the computer market place if they can get away with it. The IBM PC fundamentally brought no new technology to the industry at all. It was just repackaging and slight extension of Apple II technology, and they want it all. They absolutely want it all.\nThis market place is coming down to the two of us, whether we like it or not. I don't particularly like it, but it's coming down to Apple and IBM.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can you say that about an industry that's changing so fast? Macintosh is the hot new thing right now, but will it still be in two years? Aren't you competing with your own philosophy? Just as you're after IBM, aren't there small computer companies coming after Apple?",
    "response": "In terms of supplying the computer itself, it's coming down to Apple and IBM. And I don't think there are going to be a lot of third- and fourth-place companies, much less sixth- or seventh-place companies. Most of the new, innovative companies are focusing on the software. I think there will be lots of innovation in the areas of software but not in hardware.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "IBM might say the same thing about hardware, but you're not about to let it get away with that. Why is your point any different?",
    "response": "I think that the scale of the business has gotten large enough so that it's going to be very difficult for anyone to successfully launch anything new.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "No more billion-dollar companies hatched in garages?",
    "response": "No, I'm afraid not in computers. And this puts a responsibility on Apple, because if there's going to be innovation in this industry, it'll come from us. It's the only way we can compete with them. If we go fast enough, they can't keep up.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "When do you think IBM will finally, as you put it, fold the umbrella on the companies making IBM-compatible computers?",
    "response": "There may be some imitators left in the $100,000,000-to-$200,000,000 range, but being a $200,000,000 company is going to mean you are struggling for your life, and that's not really a position from which to innovate. Not only do I think IBM will do away with its imitators by providing software they can't provide, I think eventually it will come up with a new standard that won't even be compatible with what it's making now—because it is to limiting.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is exactly what you've done at Apple. If a person owns software for the Apple II, he can't run it on the Macintosh.",
    "response": "That's right. Mac is altogether new. We knew that we could reach the early innovators with current-generation technology—Apple II, IBM PC—because they'd stay up all night learning how to use their computer. But we'd never reach the majority of people. If we were really going to get computers to tens of millions of people, we needed a technology that would make the thing radically easier to use and more powerful at the same time, so we had to make a break. We just had to do it. We wanted to make sure it was great, because it may be the last chance that any of us get to make a clean break. And I'm very happy with the way Macintosh turned out. It will prove a really solid foundation for the next ten years.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Let's go back to the predecessors of the Lisa and the Mac, to the beginning. How influential were your parents in your interest in computers?",
    "response": "They encouraged my interests. My father was a machinist, and he was a sort of genius with his hands. He can fix anything and make it work and take any mechanical thing apart and get it back together. That was my first glimpse of it. I started to gravitate more toward electronics, and he used to get me things I could take apart and put back together. He was transferred to Palo Alto when I was five. That's how we ended up in the Valley.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "You had been adopted, hadn't you? How much of a factor in your life was that?",
    "response": "You don't ever really know, do you?",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Did you try to find your biological parents?",
    "response": "I think it's quite a natural curiosity for adopted people to want to understand where certain traits come from. But I'm mostly an environmentalist. I think the way you are raised and your values and most of your world view come from the experiences you had as you grew up. But some things aren't accounted for that way. I think it's quite natural to have a curiosity about it. And I did.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Were you successful in trying to find your natural parents?",
    "response": "That's one area I really don't want to talk about.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "The valley your parents moved to has since come to be known as Silicon Valley. What was it like growing up there?",
    "response": "It was the suburbs. It was like most suburbs in the U.S.: I grew up on a block with lots of kids. My mother taught me to read before I went to school, so I was pretty bored in school, and I turned into a little terror. You should have seen us in third grade. We basically destroyed our teacher. We would let snakes loose in the classroom and explode bombs. Things changed in the fourth grade, though. One of the saints in my life is this woman named Imogene Hill, who was a fourth-grade teacher who taught this advanced class. She got hip to my whole situation in about a month and kindled a passion in me for learning things. I learned more that year than I think I learned in any year in school. They wanted to put me in high school after that year, but my parents very wisely wouldn't let them.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "But location had something to do with your interests, didn't it? How did Silicon Valley come to be?",
    "response": "The Valley is positioned strategically between two great universities, Berkeley and Stanford. Both of those universities attract not only lots of students but very good students and ones from all over the United States. They come here and fall in love with the area and they stay here. So there is a constant influx of new, bright human resources.\nBefore World War Two, two Stanford graduates named Bill Hewlett and Dave Packard created a very innovative electronics company—Hewlett-Packard. Then the transistor was invented in 1948 by Bell Telephone Laboratories. One of the three coinventors of the transistor, William Shockley, decided to return to his home town of Palo Alto to start a little company called Shockley Labs or something. He brought with him about a dozen of the best and brightest physicists and chemists of his day. Little by little, people started breaking off and forming competitive companies, like those flowers or weeds that scatter seeds in hundreds of directions when you blow on them. And that's why the Valley is here today.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was your introduction to computers?",
    "response": "A neighbor down the block named Larry Lang was an engineer at Hewlett-Packard. He spent a lot of time with me, teaching me stuff. The first computer I ever saw was at Hewlett-Packard. They used to invite maybe ten of us down every Tuesday night and give us lectures and let us work with a computer. I was maybe 12 the first time. I remember the night. They showed us one of their new desktop computers and let us play on it. I wanted one badly.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was it about it that interested you? Did you have a sense of its potential?",
    "response": "It wasn't anything like that. I just thought they were neat. I just wanted to mess around with one.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "You went to work for Hewlett-Packard. How did that happen?",
    "response": "When I was 12 or 13, I wanted to build something and I needed some parts, so I picked up the phone and called Bill Hewlett—he was listed in the Palo Alto phone book. He answered the phone and he was real nice. He chatted with me for, like, 20 minutes. He didn't know me at all, but he ended up giving me some parts and he got me a job that summer working at Hewlett-Packard on the line, assembling frequency counters. Assembling may be too strong. I was putting in screws. It didn't matter; I was in heaven. I remember my first day, expressing my complete enthusiasm and bliss at being at Hewlett-Packard for the summer to my supervisor, a guy named Chris, telling him that my favorite thing in the whole world was electronics. I asked him what his favorite thing to do was and he looked at me and said, \"To fuck!\" [Laughs] I learned a lot that summer.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what point did you meet Steve Wozniak?",
    "response": "I met Woz when I was 13, at a friend's garage. He was about 18. He was, like, the first person I met who knew more electronics than I did at that point. We became good friends, because we shared an interest in computers and we had a sense of humor. We pulled all kinds of pranks together.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "For instance?",
    "response": "[Grins] Normal stuff. Like making a huge flag with a giant one of these on it [gives the finger]. The idea was that we would unfurl it in the middle of a school graduation. Then there was the time Wozniak made something that looked and sounded like a bomb and took it to the school cafeteria. We also went into the blue-box business together.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Those were illegal devices that allowed free long-distance phone calls, weren't they?",
    "response": "Mm-hm. The famous story about the boxes is when Woz called the Vatican and told them he was Henry Kissinger. They had someone going to wake the Pope up in the middle of the night before they figured out it wasn't really Kissinger.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Did you get into trouble for any of those things?",
    "response": "Well, I was thrown out of school a few times.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Were you then, or have you ever been, a computer nerd?",
    "response": "I wasn't completely in any one world for too long. There was so much else going on. Between my sophomore and junior years, I got stoned for the first time; I discovered Shakespeare, Dylan Thomas and all that classic stuff. I read Moby Dick and went back as a junior taking creative-writing classes. By the time I was a senior, I'd gotten permission to spend about half my time at Stanford, taking classes.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Was Wozniak obsessed at certain periods?",
    "response": "[Laughs] Yes, but not just with computers. I think Woz was in a world that nobody understood. No one shared his interests, and he was a little ahead of his time. It was very lonely for him. He's driven from inner sights rather than external expectations of him, so he survived OK. Woz and I are different in most ways, but there are some ways in which we're the same, and we're very close in those ways. We're sort of like two planets in their own orbits that every so often intersect. It wasn't just computers, either. Woz and I very much liked Bob Dylan's poetry, and we spent a lot of time thinking about a lot of that stuff. This was California. You could get LSD fresh made from Stanford. You could sleep on the beach at night with your girlfriend. California has a sense of experimentation and a sense of openness—openness to new possibilities. Besides Dylan, I was interested in Eastern mysticism, which hit the shores at about the same time. When I went to college at Reed, in Oregon, there was a constant flow of people stopping by, from Timothy Leary and Richard Alpert to Gary Snyder. There was a constant flow of intellectual questioning about the truth of life. That was a time when every college student in this country read Be Here Now and Diet for a Small Planet—there were about ten books. You'd be hard pressed to find those books on too many college campuses today. I'm not saying it's better or worse; it's just different—very different. In Search of Excellence [the book about business practices] has taken the place of Be Here Now.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "In retrospect, how did that influence what you're doing now?",
    "response": "The whole period had a huge influence. As it was clear that the Sixties were over, it was also clear that a lot of the people who had gone through the Sixties ended up not really accomplishing what they set out to accomplish, and because they had thrown their discipline to the wind, they didn't have much to fall back on. Many of my friends have ended up ingrained with the idealism of that period but also with a certain practicality, a cautiousness about ending up working behind the counter in a natural-food store when they are 45, which is what they saw happen to some of their older friends. It's not that that is bad in and of itself, but it's bad if that's not what you really wanted to do.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "After Reed, you returned to Silicon Valley and answered a now-famous ad that boasted, \"Have fun and make money.\"",
    "response": "Right. I decided I wanted to travel, but I was lacking the necessary funds. I came back down to get a job. I was looking in the paper and there was this ad that said, yes, \"Have fun and make money.\" I called. It was Atari. I had never had a job before other than the one when I was a kid. By some stroke of luck, they called me up the next day and hired me.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "That must have been at Atari's earliest stage.",
    "response": "I was, like, employee number 40. It was a very small company. They had made Pong and two other games. My first job was helping a guy named Don work on a basketball game, which was a disaster. There was this basketball game, and somebody was working on a hockey game. They were trying to model all their games after simple field sports at that time, because Pong was such a success.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "You never lost sight of the reason for the job: to earn money so you could travel.",
    "response": "Atari had shipped a bunch of games to Europe and they had some engineering defects in them, and I figured out how to fix them, but it was necessary for somebody to go over there and actually do the fixing. I volunteered to go and asked to take a leave of absence when I was there. They let me do it. I ended up in Switzerland and moved from Zurich to New Delhi. I spent some time in India.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where you shaved your head.",
    "response": "That's not quite the way it happened. I was walking around in the Himalayas and I stumbled onto this thing that turned out to be a religious festival. There was a baba, a holy man, who was the holy man of this particular festival, with his large group of followers. I could smell good food. I hadn't been fortunate enough to smell good food for a long time, so I wandered up to pay my respects and eat some lunch. For some reason, this baba, upon seeing me sitting there eating, immediately walked over to me and sat down and burst out laughing. He didn't speak much English and I spoke a little Hindi, but he tried to carry on a conversation and he was just rolling on the ground with laughter. Then he grabbed my arm and took me up this mountain trail. It was a little funny, because here were hundreds of Indians who had traveled for thousands of miles to hang out with this guy for ten seconds and I stumble in for something to eat and he's dragging me up this mountain path.\nWe get to the top of this mountain half an hour later and there's this little well and pond at the top of this mountain, and he dunks my head in the water and pulls out a razor from his pocket and starts to shave my head. I'm completely stunned. I'm 19 years old, in a foreign country, up in the Himalayas, and here is this bizarre Indian baba who has just dragged me away from the rest of the crowd, shaving my head atop this mountain peak. I'm still not sure why he did it.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What did you do when you came back?",
    "response": "Coming back was more of a culture shock than going. Well, Atari called me up and wanted me to go back to work there. I didn't really want to, but eventually they persuaded me to go back as a consultant. Wozniak and I were hanging out. He took me to some Homebrew Computer Club meetings, where computer hobbyists compared notes and stuff. I didn't find them all that exciting, but some of them were fun. Wozniak went religiously.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the thinking about computers then? Why were you interested?",
    "response": "The clubs were based around a computer kit called the Altair. It was so amazing to all of us that somebody had actually come up with a way to build a computer you could own yourself. That had never been possible. Remember, when we were in high school, neither of us had access to a computer mainframe. We had to drive somewhere and have some large company take a benevolent attitude toward us and let us use the computer. But now, for the first time, you could actually buy a computer. The Altair was a kit that came out around 1975 and sold for less than $400.\nEven though it was relatively inexpensive, not everyone could afford one. That's how the computer clubs started. People would band together and eventually become a club.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What would you do with your makeshift computers?",
    "response": "At that time, there were no graphics. It was all alphanumerics, and I used to be fascinated with the programming, simple programming. On the very early versions of computer kits, you didn't even type; you threw switches that signaled characters.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Altair, then, presented the concept of a home computer.",
    "response": "It was just sort of a computer that you could own. They really didn't know what to do with it. The first thing that they did was to put languages on it, so you could write some programs. People didn't start to apply them for practical things until a year or two later, and then it was simple things, like bookkeeping.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "And you decided you could do the Altair one better.",
    "response": "It sort of just happened. I was working a lot at Atari at night and I used to let Woz in. Atari put out a game called Gran Track, the first driving game with a steering wheel to drive it. Woz was a Gran Track addict. He would put great quantities of quarters into these games to play them, so I would just let him in at night and let him onto the production floor and he would play Gran Track all night long. When I came up against a stumbling block on a project, I would get Woz to take a break from his road rally for ten minutes and come and help me. He puttered around on some things, too. And at one point, he designed a computer terminal with video on it. At a later date, he ended up buying a microprocessor and hooking it up to the terminal and made what was to become the Apple I. Woz and I laid out the circuit board ourselves. That was basically it.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Again, the idea was just to do it?",
    "response": "Yeah, sure. And to be able to show it off to your friends.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What triggered the next step—manufacturing and selling them to make money?",
    "response": "Woz and I raised $1300 by selling my VW bus and his Hewlett-Packard calculator to finance them. A guy who started one of the first computer stores told us he could sell them if we could make them. It had not dawned on us until then.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "How did you and Wozniak work together?",
    "response": "He designed most of it. I helped on the memory part and I helped when we decided to turn it into a product. Woz isn't great at turning things into products, but he's really a brilliant designer.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Apple I was for hobbyists?",
    "response": "Completely. We sold only about 150 of them, ever. It wasn't that big a deal, but we made about $95,000 and I started to see it as a business besides something to do. Apple I was just a printed circuit board. There was no case, there was no power supply; it wasn't much of a product yet. It was just a printed circuit board. You had to go out and buy transformers for it. You had to buy your own keyboard [laughs].",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Did you and Wozniak have a vision once things started rolling? Were you both thinking about how big it could get and how computers would be able to change the world?",
    "response": "No, not particularly. Neither of us had any idea that this would go anywhere. Woz is motivated by figuring things out. He concentrated more on the engineering and proceeded to do one of his most brilliant pieces of work, which was the disk drive, another key engineering feat that made the Apple II a possibility. I was trying to build the company—trying to find out what a company was. I don't think it would have happened without Woz and I don't think it would have happened without me.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What happened to the partnership as time went on?",
    "response": "The main thing was that Woz was never really interested in Apple as a company. He was just sort of interested in getting the Apple II on a printed circuit board so he could have one and be able to carry it to his computer club without having the wires break on the way. He had done that and decided to go on to other things. He had other ideas.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Such as the US Festival rock concert and computer show, where he lost something like $10,000,000.",
    "response": "Well, I thought the US Festival was a little crazy, but Woz believed very strongly in it.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is it between the two of you now?",
    "response": "When you work with somebody that close and you go through experiences like the ones we went through, there's a bond in life. Whatever hassles you have, there is a bond. And even though he may not be your best friend as time goes on, there's still something that transcends even friendship, in a way. Woz is living his own life now. He hasn't been around Apple for about five years. But what he did will go down in history. He's going around speaking to a lot of computer events now. He likes that.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "The two of you went on to create the Apple II, which actually started the computer revolution. How did that occur?",
    "response": "It wasn't just us. We brought in other people. Wozniak still did the logic of the Apple II, which certainly is a large part of it, but there were some other key parts. The power supply was really a key. The case was really a key. The real jump with the Apple II was that it was a finished product. It was the first computer that you could buy that wasn't a kit. It was fully assembled and had its own case and its own keyboard, and you could really sit down and start to use it. And that was the breakthrough of the Apple II: that it looked like a real product.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Was the initial market hobbyists?",
    "response": "The difference was that you didn't have to be a hardware hobbyist with the Apple II. You could be a software hobbyist. That was one of the key breakthroughs with the Apple II: realizing that there were a whole lot more people who wanted to play with a computer, just like Woz and me, than there were people who could build their own. That's what the Apple II was all about. Still, the first year, we sold only 3000 or 4000.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Even that sounds like a lot for a few guys who barely knew what they were doing.",
    "response": "It was giant! We did about $200,000 when our business was in the garage, in 1976. In 1977, about $7,000,000 in business. I mean, it was phenomenal! And in 1978, we did $17,000,000. In 1979, we did $47,000,000. That's when we all really sensed that this was just going through the rafters. In 1980, we did $117,000,000. In 1981, we did $335,000,000. In 1982, we did $583,000,000. In 1983, we did $985,000,000, I think. This year, it will be a billion and a half.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "You don't forget those numbers.",
    "response": "Well, they're just yardsticks, you know. The neatest thing was, by 1979, I was able to walk into classrooms that had 15 Apple computers and see the kids using them. And those are the kinds of things that are really the milestones.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which brings us full circle to your latest milestones, the Mac and your protracted shoot-out with IBM. In this Interview, you've repeatedly sounded as if there really are only two of you left in the field. But although the two of you account for something like 60 percent of the market, can you just write off the other 40 percent—the Radio Shacks, DECs, Epsons, et al.—as insignificant? More important, are you ignoring your potentially biggest rival, A.T.&T.?",
    "response": "A.T.&T.. is absolutely going to be in the business. There is a major transformation in the company that's taking place right now. A.T.&T. is changing from a subsidized and regulated service-oriented company to a free-market, competitive-marketing technology company. A.T.&T.'s products per se have never been of the highest quality. All you have to do is go look at their telephones. They're somewhat of an embarrassment. But they do possess great technology in their research labs. Their challenge is to learn how to commercialize that technology. Also, they have to learn about consumer marketing. I think that they will do both of those things, but it's going to take them years.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Are you writing them off as a threat?",
    "response": "I don't think they're going to be a giant factor in the next 24 months, but they will learn.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What about Radio Shack?",
    "response": "Radio Shack is totally out of the picture. They have missed the boat. Radio Shack tried to squeeze the computer into their model of retailing, which in my opinion often meant selling second-rate products or low-end products in a surplus-store environment. The sophistication of the computer buyer passed Radio Shack by without their really realizing it. Their market shares dropped through the floor. I don't anticipate that they're going to recover and again become a major player.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "How about Xerox? Texas Instruments? DEC? Wang?",
    "response": "Xerox is out of the business. T.I. is doing nowhere near their expectations. As to some of the others, the large companies, like DEC and Wang, can sell to their installed bases. They can sell personal computers as advanced terminals, but that business is going to dwindle.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "How about the low-priced computers: Commodore and Atari?",
    "response": "I consider those a brochure for why you should buy an Apple II or Macintosh. I think people have already determined that the sub-$500 computers don't do very much. They either tease people to want more or frustrate people completely.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What about some of the smaller portables?",
    "response": "They are OK if you're a reporter and trying to take notes on the run. But for the average person, they're really not that useful, and there's not all that software for them, either. By the time you get your software done, a new one comes out with a slightly bigger display and your software is obsolete. So nobody is writing any software for them. Wait till we do it—the power of a Macintosh in something the size of a book!",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What about Epson and some of the Japanese computer makers?",
    "response": "I've said it before: The Japanese have hit the shores like dead fish. They're just like dead fish washing up on the shores. The Epson has been a failure in this market place.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Like computers, the automobile industry was an American industry that we almost lost to the Japanese. There is a lot of talk about American semiconductor companies' losing ground to Japanese. How will you keep the edge?",
    "response": "Japan's very interesting. Some people think it copies things. I don't think that anymore. I think what they do is reinvent things. They will get something that's already been invented and study it until they thoroughly understand it. In some cases, they understand it better than the original inventor. Out of that understanding, they will reinvent it in a more refined second-generation version. That strategy works only when what they're working with isn't changing very much—the stereo industry and the automobile industry are two examples. When the target is moving quickly, they find it very difficult, because that reinvention cycle takes a few years. As long as the definition of what a personal computer is keeps changing at the rate that it is, they will have a very hard time. Once the rate of change slows down, the Japanese will bring all of their strengths to bear on this market, because they absolutely want to dominate the computer business; there's no question about that. They see that as a national priority.\nWe think that in four to five years, the Japanese will finally figure out how to build a decent computer. And if we're going to keep this industry one in which America leads, we have four years to become world-class manufacturers. Our manufacturing technology has to equal or surpass that of the Japanese.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do you plan to accomplish that?",
    "response": "At the time we designed Macintosh, we also designed a machine to build the machine. We spent $20,000,000 building the computer industry's most automated factory. But that's not enough. Rather than take seven years to write off our factory, as most companies would do, we're writing it off in two. We will throw it away at the end of 1985 and build our second one, and we will write that off in two years and throw that away, so that three years from now, we'll be on to our third automated factory. That's the only way we can learn fast enough.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "It's not all competition with the Japanese: You buy your disk drives from Sony, for instance.",
    "response": "We buy many of our components from the Japanese. We're the largest user in the world of microprocessors, of high-technology RAM chips, of disk drives, of keyboards. We save a ton of energy not having to make and design floppy-disk drives or microprocessors that we can spend on software.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Let's talk about software. What are the revolutionary changes in software development as you've seen it in the past few years?",
    "response": "Certainly, the earlier programming, getting a programming language on a microprocessor chip, was a real breakthrough. VisiCalc was a breakthrough, because that was the first real use of computers in business, where business people could see tangible benefits of using one. Before that, you had to program your own applications, and the number of people who want to program is a small fraction—one percent. Coupled with VisiCalc, the ability to graph things, graph information, was important, and so was Lotus.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "We're dropping a lot of brand names with which people may not be familiar. Please explain them.",
    "response": "What Lotus did was combine a good spread sheet and graphics program. The word-processing and data-base parts of Lotus are certainly not the most robust that one can purchase. The real key to Lotus was that it combined spread sheet and graphics in one program, so you could go between them very rapidly. The next breakthrough is happening now, thanks to the Macintosh, which brought that Lisa technology down to an affordable price. There exists, and there will be more, revolutionary software there. You generally want to truly evaluate a breakthrough a few years after it happens.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What about word processing? You didn't mention that on the list of breakthroughs.",
    "response": "You're right, I should have listed word processing after VisiCalc. Word processing is the most universally needed application and one of the easiest to understand. It's probably the first use to which most people put their personal computer. There were word processors before personal computers, but a word processor on a personal computer was more of an economic breakthrough, while there was never any form of VisiCalc before the personal computer.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Have there been breakthroughs in educational software?",
    "response": "There has been a lot of very good software in education but not the breakthrough product, not the VisiCalc. I think that will come, but I don't expect it in the next 24 months.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "You've stressed the fact that education is a high priority for you. How do you think computers are affecting it?",
    "response": "Computers themselves, and software yet to be developed, will revolutionize the way we learn. We formed something called the Apple Education Foundation, and we give several million dollars in cash and equipment to people doing exploratory work with educational software and to schools that can't afford computers. We also wanted Macintosh to become the computer of choice in colleges, just as the Apple II is for grade and high schools. So we looked for six universities that were out to make large-scale commitments to personal computers—by large, meaning more than 1000 apiece—and instead of six, we found 24. We asked the colleges if they would invest at least $2,000,000 each to be part of the Macintosh program. All 24—including the entire Ivy League—did. So in less than a year, Macintosh has become the standard in college computing. I could ship every Macintosh we make this year just to those 24 colleges. We can't, of course, but the demand is there.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "But the software isn't there, is it?",
    "response": "Some of it's there. What's not there, the people at colleges are going to write themselves. IBM tried to stop us—I hear it formed a 400-person task force to do it—by giving away IBM PCs. But the colleges were fairly astute. They realized the software investment they were about to embark upon would far outweigh the hardware investment, and they didn't want to spend all that software money on old technology like IBM's. So in many cases, they turned down IBM's offers and went with Macintoshes. In some cases, they used IBM grant money to buy Macintoshes.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Will you name some colleges?",
    "response": "Can't. I'd get them in trouble.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "When you were in college in precomputer days, what did you and your classmates feel was the way to make a contribution? Politics?",
    "response": "None of the really bright people I knew in college went into politics. They all sensed that, in terms of making a change in the world, politics wasn't the place to be in the late Sixties and Seventies. All of them are in business now—which is funny, because they were the same people who trekked off to India or who tried in one way or another to find some sort of truth about life.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wasn't business and the lure of money merely the easy choice in the end?",
    "response": "No, none of those people care about the money. I mean, a lot of them made a lot of money, but they don't really care. Their lifestyles haven't particularly changed. It was the chance to actually try something, to fail, to succeed, to grow. Politics wasn't the place to be these past ten years if you were eager to try things out. As someone who hasn't turned 30 yet, I think your 20s are the time to be impatient, and a lot of these people's idealism would have been deeply frustrated in politics; it would have been blunted. I think it takes a crisis for something to occur in America. And I believe there's going to be a crisis of significant proportions in the early Nineties as these problems our political leaders should have been addressing boil up to the surface. And that's when a lot of these people are going to bring both their practical experience and their idealism into the political realm. You're going to see the best-trained generation ever to go into politics. They're going to know how to choose people, how to get things done, how to lead.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Doesn't every generation say that?",
    "response": "These are different times. The technological revolution is more intertwined every day with our economy and our society—more than 50 percent of America's gross national product comes from information-based industries—and most political leaders today have had no background in that revolution. It's going to become crucial that many of the larger decisions we make—how we allot our resources, how we educate our children—be made with an understanding of the technical issues and the directions the technology is taking. And that hasn't begun happening yet. In education, for example, we have close to a national embarrassment. In a society where information and innovation are going to be pivotal, there really is the possibility that America can become a second-rate industrial nation if we lose the technical momentum and leadership we have now.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "You mentioned investing in education, but isn't the problem finding the funds in a time of soaring deficits?",
    "response": "We're making the largest investment of capital that humankind has ever made in weapons over the next five years. We have decided, as a society, that that's where we should put our money, and that raises the deficits and, thus, the cost of our capital. Meanwhile, Japan, our nearest competitor on the next technological frontier—the semiconductor industry—has shaped its tax structure, its entire society, toward raising the capital to invest in that area. You get the feeling that connections aren't made in America between things like building weapons and the fact that we might lose our semiconductor industry. We have to educate ourselves to that danger.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "And you think computers will help in that process.",
    "response": "Well, I'll tell you a story. I saw a video tape that we weren't supposed to see. It was prepared for the Joint Chiefs of Staff. By watching the tape, we discovered that, at least as of a few years ago, every tactical nuclear weapon in Europe manned by U.S. personnel was targeted by an Apple II computer. Now, we didn't sell computers to the military; they went out and bought them at a dealer's, I guess. But it didn't make us feel good to know that our computers were being used to target nuclear weapons in Europe. The only bright side of it was that at least they weren't [Radio Shack] TRS-80s! Thank God for that. The point is that tools are always going to be used for certain things we don't find personally pleasing. And it's ultimately the wisdom of people, not the tools themselves, that is going to determine whether or not these things are used in positive, productive ways.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where do you see computers and software going in the near future?",
    "response": "Thus far, we're pretty much using our computers as good servants. We ask them to do something, we ask them to do some operation like a spread sheet, we ask them to take our key strokes and make a letter out of them, and they do that pretty well. And you'll see more and more perfection of that—computer as servant. But the next thing is going to be computer as guide or agent. And what that means is that it's going to do more in terms of anticipating what we want and doing it for us, noticing connections and patterns in what we do, asking us if this is some sort of generic thing we'd like to do regularly, so that we're going to have, as an example, the concept of triggers. We're going to be able to ask our computers to monitor things for us, and when certain conditions happen, are triggered, the computers will take certain actions and inform us after the fact.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "For example?",
    "response": "Simple things like monitoring your stocks every hour or every day. When a stock gets beyond set limits, the computer will call my broker and electronically sell it and then let me know. Another example is that at the end of the month, the computer will go into the data base and find all the salesmen who exceeded their sales quotas by more than 20 percent and write them a personalized letter from me and send it over the electronic mail system to them, and give me a report on who it sent the letters to each month. There will be a time when our computers have maybe 100 or so of those tasks; they're going to be much more like an agent for us. You're going to see that start to happen a little bit in the next 12 months, but really, it's about three years away. That's the next breakthrough.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Will we be able to perform all of those things on the hardware we have now? Or are you going to charge us for new machines?",
    "response": "All? That would be a dangerous statement, using the word all. I don't know about that. Macintosh was certainly designed with those concepts in mind.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "You take great pride in having Apple keep ahead. How do you feel about the older companies that have to play catch-up with the younger companies—or perish?",
    "response": "That's inevitably what happens. That's why I think death is the most wonderful invention of life. It purges the system of these old models that are obsolete. I think that's one of Apple's challenges, really. When two young people walk in with the next thing, are we going to embrace it and say this is fantastic? Are we going to be willing to drop our models, or are we going to explain it away? I think we'll do better, because we're completely aware of it and we make it a priority.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "In thinking about your success, did you ever get to the point where you slapped your head and asked yourself what was happening? After all, it was virtually overnight.",
    "response": "I used to think about selling 1,000,000 computers a year, but it was just a thought. When it actually happens, it's a totally different thing. So it was, \"Holy shit, it's actually coming true!\" But what's hard to explain is that this does not feel like overnight. Next year will be my tenth year. I had never done anything longer than a year in my life. Six months, for me, was a long time when we started Apple. So this has been my life since I've been sort of a free-willed adult. Each year has been so robust with problems and successes and learning experiences and human experiences that a year is a lifetime at Apple. So this has been ten lifetimes.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Do you know what you want to do with the rest of this lifetime?",
    "response": "There's an old Hindu saying that comes into my mind occasionally: \"For the first 30 years of your life, you make your habits. For the last 30 years of your life, your habits make you.\" As I'm going to be 30 in February, the thought has crossed my mind.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "And?",
    "response": "And I'm not sure. I'll always stay connected with Apple. I hope that throughout my life I'll sort of have the thread of my life and the thread of Apple weave in and out of each other, like a tapestry. There may be a few years when I'm not there, but I'll always come back. And that's what I may try to do. The key thing to remember about me is that I'm still a student. I'm still in boot camp. If anyone is reading any of my thoughts, I'd keep that in mind. Don't take it all too seriously. If you want to live your life in a creative way, as an artist, you have to not look back too much. You have to be willing to take whatever you've done and whoever you were and throw them away. What are we, anyway? Most of what we think we are is just a collection of likes and dislikes, habits, patterns. At the core of what we are is our values, and what decisions and actions we make reflect those values. That is why it's hard doing interviews and being visible: As you are growing and changing, the more the outside world tries to reinforce an image of you that it thinks you are, the harder it is to continue to be an artist, which is why a lot of times, artists have to go, \"Bye. I have to go. I'm going crazy and I'm getting out of here.\" And they go and hibernate somewhere. Maybe later they re-emerge a little differently.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "You could take off. You certainly don't have to worry about money. You're still working——",
    "response": "[Laughs] Because of guilt. Guilt over the money.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Let's talk about the money. You were a millionaire at 23——",
    "response": "And when I was 24, my net worth was more than $10,000,000; when I was 25, it was more than $100,000,000.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What's the main difference between having $1,000,000 and having several hundred million?",
    "response": "Visibility. The number of people who have a net worth of more than $1,000,000 in this country is in the tens of thousands. The number of people who have a net worth of more than $10,000,000 gets down to thousands. And the number who have a net worth of more than $100,000,000 gets down to a few hundred.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the money actually mean to you?",
    "response": "I still don't understand it. It's a large responsibility to have more than you can spend in your lifetime—and I feel I have to spend it. If you die, you certainly don't want to leave a large amount to your children. It will just ruin their lives. And if you die without kids, it will all go to the Government. Almost everyone would think that he could invest the money back into humanity in a much more astute way than the Government could. The challenges are to figure out how to live with it and to reinvest it back into the world, which means either giving it away or using it to express your concerns or values.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "So what do you do?",
    "response": "That's a part of my life that I like to keep private. When I have some time, I'm going to start a public foundation. I do some things privately now.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "You could spend all of your time disbursing your money.",
    "response": "Oh, you have to. I'm convinced that to give away a dollar effectively is harder than to make a dollar.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Could that be an excuse to put off doing something?",
    "response": "No. There are some simple reasons for that. One is that in order to learn how to do something well, you have to fail sometimes. In order to fail, there has to be a measurement system. And that's the problem with most philanthropy—there's no measurement system. You give somebody some money to do something and most of the time you can really never measure whether you failed or succeeded in your judgment of that person or his ideas or their implementation. So if you can't succeed or fail, it's really hard to get better. Also, most of the time, the people who come to you with ideas don't provide the best ideas. You go seek the best ideas out, and that takes a lot of time.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you plan to use your visibility to create a model for people, why is this one of the areas you choose not to discuss?",
    "response": "Because I haven't done anything much yet. In that area, actions should speak the loudest.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Are you completely virtuous or do you admit to any extravagances?",
    "response": "Well, my favorite things in life are books, sushi and.... My favorite things in life don't cost any money. It's really clear that the most precious resource we all have is time. As it is, I pay a price by not having much of a personal life. I don't have the time to pursue love affairs or to tour small towns in Italy and sit in cafes and eat tomato-and-mozzarella salad. Occasionally, I spend a little money to save myself a hassle, which means time. And that's the extent of it. I bought an apartment in New York, but it's because I love that city. I'm trying to educate myself, being from a small town in California, not having grown up with the sophistication and culture of a large city. I consider it part of my education. You know, there are many people at Apple who can buy everything that they could ever possibly want and still have most of their money unspent. I hate talking about this as a problem; people are going to read this and think, Yeah, well, give me your problem. They're going to think I'm an arrogant little asshole.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "With your wealth and past accomplishments, you have the ability to pursue dreams as few others do. Does that freedom frighten you?",
    "response": "The minute you have the means to take responsibility for your own dreams and can be held accountable for whether they come true or not, life is a lot tougher. It's easy to have wonderful thoughts when the chance to implement them is remote. When you've gotten to a place where you at least have a chance of implementing your ideas, there's a lot more responsibility in that.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "We've talked about what you see in the near future; what about the far future? If we're still in kindergarten, and you start imagining some of the ways computers are going to change our lives, what do you see?",
    "response": "When I came back from India, I found myself asking, What was the one most important thing that had struck me? And I think it was that Western rational thought is not an innate human characteristic. It is a learned ability. It had never occurred to me that if no one taught us how to think this way, we would not think this way. And yet, that's the way it is. Obviously, one of the great challenges of an education is to teach us how to think. What we're finding is that computers are actually going to affect the quality of thinking as more and more of our children have these tools available to them. Humans are tool users. What's really incredible about a book is that you can read what Aristotle wrote. You don't have to have some teacher's interpretation of Aristotle. You can certainly get that, but you can read exactly what Aristotle wrote. That direct transmission of thoughts and ideas is one of the key building blocks of why we are where we are, as a society. But the problem with a book is that you can't ask Aristotle a question. I think one of the potentials of the computer is to somehow ... capture the fundamental, underlying principles of an experience.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "For example?",
    "response": "Here's a very crude example. The original video game, Pong, captured the principles of gravity, angular momentum and things like that, to where each game obeyed those underlying principles, and yet every game was different—sort of like life. That's the simplest example. And what computer programming can do is to capture the underlying principles, the underlying essence, and then facilitate thousands of experiences based on that perception of the underlying principles. Now, what if we could capture Aristotle's world view—the underlying principles of his world view? Then you could actually ask Aristotle a question. OK. You might say it would not be exactly what Aristotle was. It could be all wrong. But maybe not.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "But you would say it was at least interesting feedback.",
    "response": "Exactly. Part of the challenge, I think, is to get these tools to millions and tens of millions of people and to start to refine these tools so that someday we can crudely, and then in a more refined sense, capture an Aristotle or an Einstein or a Land while he's alive. Imagine what that could be like for a young kid growing up. Forget the young kid—for us! And that's part of the challenge.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Will you be working on that yourself?",
    "response": "That's for someone else. It's for the next generation. I think an interesting challenge in this area of intellectual inquiry is to grow obsolete gracefully, in the sense that things are changing so fast that certainly by the end of the Eighties, we really want to turn over the reins to the next generation, whose fundamental perceptions are state-of-the-art perceptions, so that they can go on, stand on our shoulders and go much further. It's a very interesting challenge, isn't it? How to grow obsolete with grace.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 1985 Playboy"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the iPod's development process did you get a sense of how big it would become?",
    "response": "The way you can tell that you're onto something interesting is if everybody who knows about the project wants one themselves, if they can't wait to go out and open up their own wallets to buy one. That was clearly the case with the iPod. Everybody on the team wanted one.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2006 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Other companies had already tried to make a hard disk drive music player. Why did Apple get it right?",
    "response": "We had the hardware expertise, the industrial design expertise and the software expertise, including iTunes. One of the biggest insights we have was that we decided not to try to manage your music library on the iPod, but to manage it in iTunes. Other companies tried to do everything on the device itself and made it so complicated that it was useless.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2006 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the design lesson of the iPod?",
    "response": "Look at the design of a lot of consumer products—they're really complicated surfaces. We tried make something much more holistic and simple. When you first start off trying to solve a problem, the first solutions you come up with are very complex, and most people stop there. But if you keep going, and live with the problem and peel more layers of the onion off, you can oftentimes arrive at some very elegant and simple solutions. Most people just don't put in the time or energy to get there. We believe that customers are smart, and want objects which are well thought through.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2006 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Some people say that iPod might lose its cachet because it's too popular—how can it be cool when Dick Cheney and Queen Elizabeth have one?",
    "response": "That's like saying you don't want to kiss your lover's lips because everyone has lips. It doesn't make any sense. We don't strive to appear cool. We just try to make the best products we can. And if they are cool, well, that's great.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2006 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "What products, maybe outside technology, do you consider cool?",
    "response": "I like things that do the job and kind of disappear into my life. Like Levis. They just kind of get faded and disappear, and you don't think about it much. If you look, you appreciate the design, but you feel something from them, too. A lot of quality is communicated through a feeling that people have. They don't understand exactly why, but they know that a lot of care and love was put into the designing of the product.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2006 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Let's talk about the iTunes store. How did you get the record labels, which had been resisting digital music, to sign up?",
    "response": "It was a process over 18 months. We got to know these folks and we made a series of predictions that a lot of things they were trying would fail. Then they went and tried them, and they all failed, for the reasons that we had predicted. We kept coming back to visit them every month or two, and they started to believe that we might actually have some insight into this, and our credibility grew with them to the point where they were willing to take a chance with us. Now, remember, it was initially just on the Mac, so one of the arguments that we used was, \"If we're completely wrong and you completely screw up the entire music market for Mac owners, the sandbox is small enough that you really won't damage the overall music industry very much.\" That was one instance where Macintosh's [small] market share helped us. Then about six months later we were able to successfully persuade them to take down the barriers and let us move it out to the whole market.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2006 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Now people at some labels think that iTunes, with its dominant market share has too much power.",
    "response": "We've never once gone to them and asked them to lower their prices.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2006 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "No, but you've asked them not to raise their prices, when some of them wanted to.",
    "response": "Our core initial strategy on the store was that if you want to stop piracy, the way to stop it is by competing with it, by offering a better product at a fair price. In essence, we would make a deal with people. If they would pay a fair price, we would give them a better product and they would stop being pirates. And it worked. If we go back now and we raise prices—this is what we told the record companies last year—we will be violating that implicit deal. Many [users] will say, \"I knew it all along that the music companies were gonna screw me, and now they're screwing me.\" And they would never buy anything from iTunes again.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2006 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Do you think that it's fair to the customer that the songs they buy from Apple will only work on iTunes and the iPod?",
    "response": "Well, they knew that all along.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2006 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "At one point you were saying, \"When our customers demand it, that's when we'll consider interoperability.\"",
    "response": "Nobody's ever demanded it. People know up front that when they buy music from the iTunes music store it plays on iPods, and so we're not trying to hide anything there.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2006 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "Microsoft has announced its new iPod competitor, Zune. It says that this device is all about building communities. Are you worried?",
    "response": "In a word, no. I've seen the demonstrations on the Internet about how you can find another person using a Zune and give them a song they can play three times. It takes forever. By the time you've gone through all that, the girl's got up and left! You're much better off to take one of your earbuds out and put it in her ear. Then you're connected with about two feet of headphone cable.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2006 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "IPods now have video, games, audio books and podcasts. Will iPods always be about the music?",
    "response": "Who knows? But it's hard to imagine that music is not the epicenter of the iPod, for a long, long, long, long, long time. I was very lucky to grow up in a time when music really mattered. It wasn't just something in the background; it really mattered to a generation of kids growing up. It really changed the world. I think that music faded in importance for a while, and the iPod has helped to bring music back into people's lives in a really meaningful way. Music is so deep within all of us, but it's easy to go for a day or a week or a month or a year without really listening to music. And the iPod has changed that for tens of millions of people, and that makes me really happy, because I think music is good for the soul.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2006 Newsweek"
  },
  {
    "question": "On the birth of the iPhone",
    "response": "We all had cellphones. We just hated them, they were so awful to use. The software was terrible. The hardware wasn't very good. We talked to our friends, and they all hated their cellphones too. Everybody seemed to hate their phones. And we saw that these things really could become much more powerful and interesting to license. It's a huge market. I mean a billion phones get shipped every year, and that's almost an order of magnitude greater than the number of music players. It's four times the number of PCs that ship every year.\nIt was a great challenge. Let's make a great phone that we fall in love with. And we've got the technology. We've got the miniaturization from the iPod. We've got the sophisticated operating system from Mac. Nobody had ever thought about putting operating systems as sophisticated as OS X inside a phone, so that was a real question. We had a big debate inside the company whether we could do that or not. And that was one where I had to adjudicate it and just say, 'We're going to do it. Let's try.' The smartest software guys were saying they can do it, so let's give them a shot. And they did.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On Apple's connection with the consumer",
    "response": "We did iTunes because we all love music. We made what we thought was the best jukebox in iTunes. Then we all wanted to carry our whole music libraries around with us. The team worked really hard. And the reason that they worked so hard is because we all wanted one. You know? I mean, the first few hundred customers were us.\n\nIt's not about pop culture, and it's not about fooling people, and it's not about convincing people that they want something they don't. We figure out what we want. And I think we're pretty good at having the right discipline to think through whether a lot of other people are going to want it, too. That's what we get paid to do.\nSo you can't go out and ask people, you know, what the next big [thing.] There's a great quote by Henry Ford, right? He said, 'If I'd have asked my customers what they wanted, they would have told me A faster horse. ' ",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On choosing strategy",
    "response": "We do no market research. We don't hire consultants. The only consultants I've ever hired in my 10 years is one firm to analyze Gateway's retail strategy so I would not make some of the same mistakes they made [when launching Apple's retail stores]. But we never hire consultants, per se. We just want to make great products.\nWhen we created the iTunes Music Store, we did that because we thought it would be great to be able to buy music electronically, not because we had plans to redefine the music industry. I mean, it just seemed like writing on the wall, that eventually all music would be distributed electronically. That seemed obvious because why have the cost? The music industry has huge returns. Why have all this [overhead] when you can just send electrons around easily?",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On what drives Apple employees",
    "response": "We don't get a chance to do that many things, and every one should be really excellent. Because this is our life. Life is brief, and then you die, you know? So this is what we've chosen to do with our life. We could be sitting in a monastery somewhere in Japan. We could be out sailing. Some of the [executive team] could be playing golf. They could be running other companies. And we've all chosen to do this with our lives. So it better be damn good. It better be worth it. And we think it is.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On why people want to work at Apple:",
    "response": "The reason is, is because you can't do what you can do at Apple anywhere else. The engineering is long gone in most PC companies. In the consumer electronics companies, they don't understand the software parts of it. And so you really can't make the products that you can make at Apple anywhere else right now. Apple's the only company that has everything under one roof.\n\nThere's no other company that could make a MacBook Air and the reason is that not only do we control the hardware, but we control the operating system. And it is the intimate interaction between the operating system and the hardware that allows us to do that. There is no intimate interaction between Windows and a Dell notebook.\n\nOur DNA is as a consumer company -- for that individual customer who's voting thumbs up or thumbs down. That's who we think about. And we think that our job is to take responsibility for the complete user experience. And if it's not up to par, it's our fault, plain and simply.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On whether Apple could live without him",
    "response": "We've got really capable people at Apple. I made Tim [Cook] COO and gave him the Mac division and he's done brilliantly. I mean, some people say, 'Oh, God, if [Jobs] got run over by a bus, Apple would be in trouble.' And, you know, I think it wouldn't be a party, but there are really capable people at Apple. And the board would have some good choices about who to pick as CEO. My job is to make the whole executive team good enough to be successors, so that's what I try to do.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On his demanding reputation:",
    "response": "My job is to not be easy on people. My job is to make them better. My job is to pull things together from different parts of the company and clear the ways and get the resources for the key projects. And to take these great people we have and to push them and make them even better, coming up with more aggressive visions of how it could be.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On Apple's focus",
    "response": "Apple is a $30 billion company, yet we've got less than 30 major products. I don't know if that's ever been done before. Certainly the great consumer electronics companies of the past had thousands of products. We tend to focus much more. People think focus means saying yes to the thing you've got to focus on. But that's not what it means at all. It means saying no to the hundred other good ideas that there are. You have to pick carefully.\n\nI'm actually as proud of many of the things we haven't done as the things we have done. The clearest example was when we were pressured for years to do a PDA, and I realized one day that 90% of the people who use a PDA only take information out of it on the road. They don't put information into it. Pretty soon cellphones are going to do that, so the PDA market's going to get reduced to a fraction of its current size, and it won't really be sustainable. So we decided not to get into it. If we had gotten into it, we wouldn't have had the resources to do the iPod. We probably wouldn't have seen it coming.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On his management style",
    "response": "We've got 25,000 people at Apple. About 10,000 of them are in the stores. And my job is to work with sort of the top 100 people, that's what I do. That doesn't mean they're all vice presidents. Some of them are just key individual contributors. So when a good idea comes, you know, part of my job is to move it around, just see what different people think, get people talking about it, argue with people about it, get ideas moving among that group of 100 people, get different people together to explore different aspects of it quietly, and, you know - just explore things.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On finding talent:",
    "response": "When I hire somebody really senior, competence is the ante. They have to be really smart. But the real issue for me is, Are they going to fall in love with Apple? Because if they fall in love with Apple, everything else will take care of itself. They'll want to do what's best for Apple, not what's best for them, what's best for Steve, or anybody else.\n\nRecruiting is hard. It's just finding the needles in the haystack. We do it ourselves and we spend a lot of time at it. I've participated in the hiring of maybe 5,000-plus people in my life. So I take it very seriously. You can't know enough in a one-hour interview. So, in the end, it's ultimately based on your gut. How do I feel about this person? What are they like when they're challenged? Why are they here? I ask everybody that: 'Why are you here?' The answers themselves are not what you're looking for. It's the meta-data.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On the benefits of owning an operating system",
    "response": "That allows us to innovate at a much faster rate than if we had to wait for Microsoft, like Dell and HP and everybody else does. Because Microsoft has their own timetable, for probably good reasons. I mean Vista took what — seven or eight years? It's hard to get your new feature that you need for your new hardware if it has to wait eight years. So we can set our own priorities and look at things in a more holistic way from the point of view of the customer. It also means that we can take it and we can make a version of it to fit in the iPhone and the iPod. And, you know, we certainly couldn't do that if we didn't own it.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On his marathon Monday meetings",
    "response": "When you hire really good people you have to give them a piece of the business and let them run with it. That doesn't mean I don't get to kibitz a lot. But the reason you're hiring them is because you're going to give them the reins. I want [them] making as good or better decisions than I would. So the way to do that is to have them know everything, not just in their part of the business, but in every part of the business.\n\nSo what we do every Monday is we review the whole business. We look at what we sold the week before. We look at every single product under development, products we're having trouble with, products where the demand is larger than we can make. All the stuff in development, we review. And we do it every single week. I put out an agenda -- 80% is the same as it was the last week, and we just walk down it every single week.\nWe don't have a lot of process at Apple, but that's one of the few things we do just to all stay on the same page.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On dealing with roadblocks",
    "response": "At Pixar when we were making Toy Story, there came a time when we were forced to admit that the story wasn't great. It just wasn't great. We stopped production for five months.... We paid them all to twiddle their thumbs while the team perfected the story into what became Toy Story. And if they hadn't had the courage to stop, there would have never been a Toy Story the way it is, and there probably would have never been a Pixar.\n\nWe called that the 'story crisis,' and we never expected to have another one. But you know what? There's been one on every film. We don't stop production for five months. We've gotten a little smarter about it. But there always seems to come a moment where it's just not working, and it's so easy to fool yourself - to convince yourself that it is when you know in your heart that it isn't.\n\nWell, you know what? It's been that way with [almost] every major project at Apple, too.... Take the iPhone. We had a different enclosure design for this iPhone until way too close to the introduction to ever change it. And I came in one Monday morning, I said, 'I just don't love this. I can't convince myself to fall in love with this. And this is the most important product we've ever done.'\n\nAnd we pushed the reset button. We went through all of the zillions of models we'd made and ideas we'd had. And we ended up creating what you see here as the iPhone, which is dramatically better. It was hell because we had to go to the team and say, 'All this work you've [done] for the last year, we're going to have to throw it away and start over, and we're going to have to work twice as hard now because we don't have enough time.' And you know what everybody said? 'Sign us up.'\nThat happens more than you think, because this is not just engineering and science. There is art, too. Sometimes when you're in the middle of one of these crises, you're not sure you're going to make it to the other end. But we've always made it, and so we have a certain degree of confidence, although sometimes you wonder. I think the key thing is that we're not all terrified at the same time. I mean, we do put our heart and soul into these things.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On the iPod tipping point",
    "response": "It was difficult for a while because for various reasons the Mac had not been accepted by a lot of people, who went with Windows. And we were just working really hard, and our market share wasn't going up. It makes you wonder sometimes whether you're wrong. Maybe our stuff isn't better, although we thought it was. Or maybe people don't care, which is even more depressing.\n\nIt turns out with the iPod we kind of got out from that operating-system glass ceiling and it was great because [it showed that] Apple innovation, Apple engineering, Apple design did matter. The iPod captured 70% market share. I cannot tell you how important that was after so many years of laboring and seeing a 4% to 5% market share on the Mac. To see something like that happen with the iPod was a great shot in the arm for everybody.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On what they did next:",
    "response": "We made more. We worked harder. We said: 'This is great. Let's do more.' I mean, the Mac market share is going up every single quarter. We're growing four times faster than the industry. People are starting to pay a little more attention. We've helped it along. We put Intel processors in and we can run PC apps alongside Mac apps. We helped it along. But I think a lot of it is people have finally started to realize that they don't have to put up with Windows - that there is an alternative. I think nobody really thought about it that way before.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On launching the Apple store",
    "response": "It was very simple. The Mac faithful will drive to a destination, right? They'll drive somewhere special just to do that. But people who own Windows - we want to convert them to Mac. They will not drive somewhere special. They don't think they want a Mac. They will not take the risk of a 20-minute drive in case they don't like it.\n\nBut if we put our store in a mall or on a street that they're walking by, and we reduce that risk from a 20-minute drive to 20 footsteps, then they're more likely to go in because there's really no risk. So we decided to put our stores in high-traffic locations. And it works.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On catching tech's next wave",
    "response": "Things happen fairly slowly, you know. They do. These waves of technology, you can see them way before they happen, and you just have to choose wisely which ones you're going to surf. If you choose unwisely, then you can waste a lot of energy, but if you choose wisely it actually unfolds fairly slowly. It takes years.\nOne of our biggest insights [years ago] was that we didn't want to get into any business where we didn't own or control the primary technology because you'll get your head handed to you.\nWe realized that almost all - maybe all - of future consumer electronics, the primary technology was going to be software. And we were pretty good at software. We could do the operating system software. We could write applications on the Mac or even PC, like iTunes. We could write the software in the device, like you might put in an iPod or an iPhone or something. And we could write the back-end software that runs on a cloud, like iTunes.\n\nSo we could write all these different kinds of software and make it work seamlessly. And you ask yourself, What other companies can do that? It's a pretty short list. The reason that we were very excited about the phone, beyond that fact that we all hated our phones, was that we didn't see anyone else who could make that kind of contribution. None of the handset manufacturers really are strong in software.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On failing, so far, with Apple TV",
    "response": "Here's how I look at it. Everybody's tried to make a great product for the living room. Microsoft's tried, we've tried -- everybody's tried. And everybody's failed. We failed, so far.\n\nSo there's a whole bunch of people that have tried, and every single one of them's failed, including us. And that's why I call it a hobby. It's not a business yet, it's a hobby.\n\nWe've come out with our second try -- 'Apple TV, Take 2' is what we call it internally. We realized that the first product we did was about helping you view the content of whatever you had in iTunes on your Mac or PC, and wirelessly sending it to your widescreen TV.\n\nWell, it turns out that's not what people really wanted to do. I mean, yeah, it's nice to see your photos up on the big screen. That's frosting on the cake, but it's not the cake. What everybody really wanted, it turned out, was movies.\n\nSo we began the process of talking to Hollywood studios and were able to get all the major studios to license their movies for rental. And we only have about 600 movies so far ingested on iTunes, but we'll have thousands later this year. We lowered the price to $229. And we'll see how it does. Will this resonate and be something that you just can't live without and love? We'll see. I think it's got a shot.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "On managing through the economic downturn",
    "response": "We've had one of these before, when the dot-com bubble burst. What I told our company was that we were just going to invest our way through the downturn, that we weren't going to lay off people, that we'd taken a tremendous amount of effort to get them into Apple in the first place -- the last thing we were going to do is lay them off. And we were going to keep funding. In fact we were going to up our R&D budget so that we would be ahead of our competitors when the downturn was over. And that's exactly what we did. And it worked. And that's exactly what we'll do this time.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2008 Fortune"
  },
  {
    "question": "\"Rip. Mix. Burn.\" [a tagline from Apple advertising of the time] has been Apple's mantra as of late.  Why go legit now?",
    "response": "\"Rip. Mix. Burn.\" was never not legit. When some folks thought \"Rip. Mix. Burn.\" was an anthem to steal music, it was just because they didn't know what they were talking about. They obviously didn't have any kids living at home. This was the 50 year-old-crowd that thought that. We've been against stealing music since the beginning. We own a lot of intellectual property. Most of competitors don't, but we do. We're not happy when people steal. So, this is not an about face for us, or anything like that. We've been consistent from the beginning. \"Rip. Mix. Burn.\" never meant go steal music—it meant rip, mix, burn—exactly what it said.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2011 Technologizer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Any regrets or remorse about how the tagline \"Rip. Mix. Burn.\" may have been misinterpreted?",
    "response": "No, not really, it certainly got people thinking about Apple and music I guess. It was frustrating at times when people didn't know what it meant, but everyone under 30 knew what it meant, so that was probably what really counted.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2011 Technologizer"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do you think Apple's new music service will change the digital music landscape?",
    "response": "With the introduction of the new iTunes Music Store we've now built the first real complete ecosystem for the digital music age. We've got a way to buy music online legally that's fantastic—it's better than any other way to acquire music. We've got a way to manage music with the iTunes Jukebox, which is the best in the world. And we've got a way to listen to music on the go with the iPod—which is the most popular MP3 player in the world—and the coolest, one of the coolest things in the world. So we've really got, from one end to another, a complete solution for digital music. We're the only people in the world to do this, so we feel great about it.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2011 Technologizer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Do you think you'll be able to sway the tens of millions who use the unauthorized services?",
    "response": "Well, I don't know. We'll find out. But this is really a far better experience. Not only do the downloads not crap out half way through, and not only is it perfectly encoded—instead of having the last four seconds cut off—but offering previews of every song in the store is just giant, it's giant. Just click a button and you're hearing a preview. It's really cool. And it allows you to explore music in a way that no download service has ever done to date. And the ability to browse—you can't do that with Kazaa, you can't do any of this stuff with Kazaa, the experience is so much better than Kazaa, I think a lot of people don't want to spend 15 minutes downloading a song and getting a less than perfect quality song when they're all done, and without a preview, finding out it's the wrong song by the time they're done.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2011 Technologizer"
  },
  {
    "question": "What about subscription services?",
    "response": "Well, they've failed. They've completely failed. Nobody wants to rent their music. They have hardly any subscribers.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2011 Technologizer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Any projected usage stats on iTunes Music Store you can share?",
    "response": "You know, we have some internally. But who knows? We have no idea. I'm waiting for some data today, actually. We were swamped earlier, so I heard.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2011 Technologizer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Some detractors like those at Listen.com say that downloading isn't the most popular feature on their music service Rhapsody. What's your response? ",
    "response": "Well, that's correct. Downloading sucks on their service. You download a track and you can't burn it to a CD without paying them more money—you can't put it on your MP3 player, you can't put it on multiple computers—it sucks!  So of course nobody downloads! You pay extra to download even on top of subscription fees. No wonder they have hardly any download traffic—[they] hardly even have any subscribers.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2011 Technologizer"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Wall Street Journal recently fashioned you as a \"digital music impresario,\" how do you feel about that?",
    "response": "I didn't know what it meant. Does that mean I run a carnival? What we do at Apple is very simple: we invent stuff. We make the best personal computers in the world, some of the best software, the best portable MP3/music player, and now we make the best online music store in the world. We just make stuff. So I don't know what impresario means. We make stuff, put it out there, and people use it.Clearly, we've been leading the revolution. The personal computer is changing—it's changing into this digital hub for a digital lifestyle—so we've been leading that change, we're not followers, we've lead that charge. Digital moviemaking, DVD burning, digital photography, and of course, digital music. So we are in the forefront.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2011 Technologizer"
  },
  {
    "question": "What's next?",
    "response": "I think what's next for me is getting a good night's sleep... I don't know... We have all sorts [of things] that we work on, but we never really talk about what's next until we're ready...",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2011 Technologizer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Can you say anything about the Music Store's development costs or Apple's investment?",
    "response": "Well, we don't usually talk about that, but all I would say is that... you know I had somebody comment today, \"Well, now that you have introduced your store, do you expect a lot others?\" And I guess our answer is no. This is really hard. Just to create an infrastructure to pump oceans of bits out in the world, you know, we've done that over the last several years with movie trailers and stuff, and that's tens of millions of dollars for server farms and networking farms 'it's huge' and we've already got that in place, and say you want to have millions of transactions, and our online store is all tied into SAP and auditors bless it, and to do that, that's tens of millions of dollars, and we have one-click shopping, and only us and Amazon have that, and then to make a jukebox, if you don't a popular jukebox, how much does it cost to make iTunes and make it popular? A lot! But we've got that.And then iPod, if you want to make an iPod, what does that cost? Well, nobody has done it but us, people have tried, but they haven't even come close. That's a lot of money. So we've already made these investments and we can leverage all these investments. And then we've invested more on top of that to make a store. But to recreate this, it's tens of millions of dollars and years. That's why I don't think this is going to be so easy to copy.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2011 Technologizer"
  },
  {
    "question": "How tough was it to sell your music service concept to music industry executives?",
    "response": "Well, we started almost a year and a half ago, and as you recall, the climate at that time was more hostile than it is today, but we did have the luxury of going in at the top, so I talked to Roger Aims at Warner, Doug Morris at Universal, and the other guys. And they clearly realized that the Internet was in their future, but they were shell-shocked with Napster and people stealing their content. And so, the major discussions with the labels were really over giving the users broad personal use rights. And we worked through that, and they learned. I think they trusted us to do the right thing. You know most everybody in the music industry uses a Mac—and they all have iPods—even the ones who don't use a computer have somebody else load up their iPods for 'em with the songs they want.So I think they see Apple as the most creative of the technical companies, a very artist-friendly company, very credible. And you know, we were able to negotiate landmark deals with them that no one else has ever come close to in terms of offering the user really broad rights to the music they buy.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2011 Technologizer"
  },
  {
    "question": "What about independent labels, will they follow suit?",
    "response": "Yes. They've already been calling us like crazy. We've had to put most of them off until after launch just because the major big five have most of the music, and we only had so many hours in the day. But now we're really going to have time to focus on a lot of the independents and that will be really great.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2011 Technologizer"
  },
  {
    "question": "With iTunes Music Store, the artists win, music labels win, but what about traditional retailers?",
    "response": "You should go ask them. The Internet was made to deliver music.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2011 Technologizer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Anything else you would like to add? ",
    "response": "It's so great! I cannot overemphasize that because of the previews, browsing, etc. you fall in love with music again—and you find the hits you've heard before and the gems you've never heard before—and it's really wonderful.  It's so cool.",
    "interview_name": "Steve Jobs: 2011 Technologizer"
  }
]